<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Spiritual physicke to cure the diseases of the soule, arising from superfluitie of choller, prescribed out of Gods word Wherein the chollericke man may see the dangerousnesse of this disease of the soule vniust anger, the preseruatiues to keepe him from the infection thereof, and also fit medicines to restore him to health beeing alreadie subiect to this raging passion. Profitable for all to vse, seeing all are patients in this desease of impatiencie.</title>
            <author>Downame, John, d. 1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845454</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10356</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10356)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 289:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Spiritual physicke to cure the diseases of the soule, arising from superfluitie of choller, prescribed out of Gods word Wherein the chollericke man may see the dangerousnesse of this disease of the soule vniust anger, the preseruatiues to keepe him from the infection thereof, and also fit medicines to restore him to health beeing alreadie subiect to this raging passion. Profitable for all to vse, seeing all are patients in this desease of impatiencie.</title>
                  <author>Downame, John, d. 1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36, 35-81, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Gabriel Simson for William Iones, dwelling neare Holborne Conduict at the signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Dovvname.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A treatise of anger.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anger --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10356:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10356:1"/>
            <p> Spiritual phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke to cure the diſeaſes <hi>of the ſoule, ariſing from</hi> ſuperfluitie of choller, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>out of Gods word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the chollericke man may ſee <hi>the dangerouſneſſe of this diſeaſe of the ſoule</hi> vniuſt anger, the preſeruatiues to keepe <hi>him from the infection thereof, and</hi> alſo fit medicines to reſtore him to health beeing alreadie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to this raging paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Profitable for all to vſe, ſeeing all are pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents</hi> in this diſeaſe of impatiencie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Habet et muſca ſplene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et ſua formicae bilis ineſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PRO. 16. 32.</bibl>
               <p>He that is flow to anger is better then the mightie man: and he that ruleth his owne minde, is better then he that winneth a Cytie.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Gabriel Simſon</hi> for William Iones, <hi>dwelling neare Holborne</hi> Conduict at the ſigne of the Gun. 1600.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10356:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10356:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT honourable ſir <hi>Thomas Egerton</hi> knight, Lord <hi>Keeper of the great ſeale</hi> of England, and one of her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties honour able priuie counſell, my</hi> very good Lord: health and <hi>proſperitie with increaſe of all</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall graces in this life, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happineſſe in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING HAD through your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable bounty, a part of the Lords Vineyarde allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto mee his moſt vnwoorthy woorkeman, by your Honour his moſt woorthy ſteward, to the end I ſhould plant and water, purge and prune it, I thought it my parte not onely to performe my dutie in this behalfe, in ſuch meaſure as God
<pb facs="tcp:10356:3"/> enableth me, but alſo to preſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your honour the firſt fruits of my labor which haue yet offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to publike view, to the end that I might thereby both ſhew my ſelfe not altogeather negligent in our great Lord and maiſters buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and alſo giue ſome token of moſt obliged duty and humble thankefulneſſe to you his honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſteward, by whoſe appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I haue obtained a place wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I may imploy my paynes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as otherwiſe I ſhould eyther haue ſtood idle in the market place, or els beene compelled to haue digged in another mans ground, with great labour &amp; little fruit. If theſe my firſt fruits ſeeme vnpleaſant in your moſt learned and iudiciall taſte, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impute it to the immaturitie cauſed by their ſhort time of grouth and ſmall-experienced skill of the vintager, or els conſider that they
<pb facs="tcp:10356:3"/> are deſtinated to a phyſicall vſe for the purging away of choller, and therefore though they be not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in taſt, yet may they be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Such as they are (in all humilitie, crauing pardon for my bouldnes) I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend them to your honourable patronage and protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your ſelfe to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, moſt hartily beſeching the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and great Lord of the vinyard long to continue you his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſteward amongſt vs, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of his glory, the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of his vine, and the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding comfort of his poore contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned labourers. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours in all humble duty moſt bounden. <hi>IOHN DOVVNAME.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10356:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall infection of this contagious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of the ſoule vniuſt anger, and the manifould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious euils which it worketh, both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and publique, I thought good to preſcribe out of Gods word, ſome reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for thoſe patients which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my cure, whereby they might eyther be preſerued from theſe feuer-like fits, which cauſe men outwardly to ſhake, and tremble when as inwardly they are moſt inflamed; or els haue their heate ſomewhat allayed and abated when they are alreadie fallen into them. The which my preſcript I thought at the firſt ſhould haue beene communicated to no more then mine owne patients, till I was perſwaded by more ſkilfull Phyſitions then my ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:10356:4"/> that the publiſhing thereof might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downd to others profit. And therefore deſiring nothing more then to exerciſe my poore talent to the glory of my mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter who beſtowed it, and the benefit of my fellow ſeruants, for whoſe good alſo I haue receiued it, I willingly condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their motion. And for as much, as I had onely ſhadowed a rude draught without colour or countenance, I was fayne to take a reueiw of my woorke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering ſome things, and adding others as it were new lineaments, which I thought more fit for the Preſſe then for the Pulpit. If any thinke me too quick in practiſe, they will (I hope) excuſe me, if they conſider that I make experience of my ſlender ſkil, not in the vital parts, but in the feete of the ſoule, namely the affections, and yet the curing of them, or but this one of them, may greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the benefit of the whole, for as the diſeaſes of the feete doe grieue the hart and offend the head, and the curing
<pb facs="tcp:10356:5"/> and healing of them doth eaſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort both, ſo when the affections are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered beeing infected with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of our originall corruption, euen the chiefe parts of the ſoule the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding &amp; wil, are not a little diſturbed and diſordered, by receiuing from them their contagious pollutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And therfore he who can ſkilfully purge theſe neather parts ſhall eaſe the higher, by drawing downe thoſe corrupt humors which do offend and annoy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Seeing then there may come by my practiſe great good with little danger, I haue the rather ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured the cure: beeing contented to vndergoe the cenſure of ſome for too much haſt, who (I feare me) are in theſe caſes as much too ſlow, to the end that I may to the vttermoſt of my ſkill benefit many. The Lord who is the onely true Phyſition of ſoules diſeaſed with ſinne, bleſſe this and all other my indeauours that they may be profitable for the ſetting forth of his glory, the benefit of my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and furthering the aſſurance of mine owne ſaluation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10356:5"/>
            <head>Spirituall phyſick to cure <hi>the diſeaſes of the ſoule, ariſing from</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie of choller preſcribed out of <hi>Gods word.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Epheſians 4. 26.</bibl>
               <q>Be angry and ſinne not, let not the ſunne go downe on your wrath.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He miſerable ruines of our excellent ſtate by creation which were the lamentable effects following the ſinne of our firſt parents: and the fowle ſpots of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall corruption, which like a contagious leproſie deriued from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue infected all their poſteritie, do not ſo euidently appeare in any part of the body or foule as in the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which are ſo corrupted and diſordered that there ſcarce remaine any ſmall reliques of their created puritie. And hence it is that the Heathen Philoſophers though they did
<pb facs="tcp:10356:6"/> not perceiue how much the bright ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning beames of our reaſon, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding part of the ſoule, were dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and darkned with the foggie miſts of originall ſinne, but highly extolled with ouer parciall prayſes, the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and perfection of them, yet they playnely diſcerned the great corruption of our diſordered affections in ſo much that ſome of them being ouerſwayed with too great vehemencie of affection in ſpeaking agaynſt the affections haue condemned them as ſimply, and in their owne nature euill, and therfore wholy to be abandoned, ſeeing there was no hope they ſhould be amended: others with a more iudiciall inſight diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning betweene the things themſelues &amp; their corruption, haue written whole tractates for the reforming of them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming the chiefe top and perfection of wiſdom to conſiſt in the well gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ordering of theſe diſordered and tumultuous paſſions.</p>
                  <p>If then the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Philoſophers walking in the darke night of ignorance &amp; error, and illightened only with a ſmall glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering ſparke of naturall reaſon, could
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10356:6"/> thereby both diſcerne their corruption and alſo did ſtudy to reforme and bring them vnder the rule of reaſon, how much more earneſtly ſhould we ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor, not ſo much to marſhall them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duict of naturall reaſon, which is it ſelf but a blind leader, as to reforme and purge them by the worde of God, which like a glorious ſhyning ſunne, hath diſpelled the foggy miſts of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and error, and ſo diſcouered all the ſpottes and deformities of them, farre more clearely then our blinde rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                  <p>And as we are earneſtly to labor for the reforming of all the affections, ſo moſt earneſtly of al this of anger, which of all other is moſt turbulent and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent if it be not bridled and reſtrayned. And for our better furtherance in ſo good an endeuor, I haue made choice of this text, to the end I might ſhew how far forth anger is to be aprooued &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, and in what reſpect it is to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoided and ſhunned.</p>
                  <p>In handling wherof I wil firſt ſhew the meaning of the words, and afterwards intreate of their ſeuerall parts.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10356:7"/>
                  <p> In ſhewing the meaning of the words I will firſt define what anger is, and then <note place="margin">What an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is in generall.</note> ſet downe the diuers ſorts therof. Anger therfore generallie conſidered is thus defined: it is an affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby the bloud about the hart being heated by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of ſome iniury offered to a mans ſelfe or his friends, <hi>&amp;</hi> that in truth or in his opinion onely, the appetite is ſtirred vp to take reuenge. <note place="margin">The names of anger with the notation.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt wee will ſpeake of the thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined. and after of the definition. Anger in the latin tongue is called <hi>(ira)</hi> wich name hath his notation from the effect, for when by the apprehenſion of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury the hart is inflamed with the heate of anger, it doth make a man <hi>(quaſi ex ſe ire) as it were to goe out of himſelfe,</hi> and in this reſpect he who was angry was ſaid by an vſuall Latin phraſe <hi>(non eſse apud ſe, not to be with himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>ad ſe rediiſſe, to haue returned to himſelfe,</hi> when his anger was paſſed ouer. The <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> did eſpecially vſe two names to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this affection, which did contayne in them the very nature of anger. The firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which ſignifieth the preturba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion it ſelf, or the heating of the bloud by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10356:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> the apprehenſion of the iniury offered, tother <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which ſignifieth the appetite or deſire of reuenge which followeth the the perturbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that theſe two names contayne in them, both the materiall &amp; formall cauſe of anger: for the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cauſe is the heating of the bloud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the hart which is ſignified by the firſt name <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: the formall cauſe is the appetite or deſire of reuenging the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury offered, which is vnderſtod by the other name <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>The moſt vſuall name vſed by the <hi>Hebrues</hi> to ſignifie anger is <hi>Aph.</hi> which ſignifieth alſo the Noſe, and by a ſynec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doche the whole face: which name is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto it either becauſe in a mans an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the breath doth more vehementlie and often iſſue out of the noſe, which is as it were the ſmoke iſſuing from the flame kindled about the hart, or els be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the face anger is ſooneſt diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the often entercourſe <hi>&amp;</hi> change of collours.</p>
                  <p>Our Engliſh word anger is deriued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the latin word <hi>Angor,</hi> which either ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth throtling <hi>&amp;</hi> choking, or vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>&amp;</hi> grief, becauſe anger worketh both theſe effects if it be immoderat: for it ſtops the
<pb facs="tcp:10356:8"/> throate leauing no paſſage for words, and it vexeth and tormenteth both the body and the minde.</p>
                  <p>And ſo much for the name: now we wil <note place="margin">The defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</note> ſpeake of the definition. Firſt I ſay it is an affection: for the whole eſſence of a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n conſiſteth of theſe 3. things, body, ſoule, and affections, which doe partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of both the other now anger can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be a qualitie or propertie of the ſoule alone, for the materiall cauſe thereof is the boyling of the bloud about the hart, nor of the body alone, for the formall cauſe, namely the appetite and deſire of reuenge ſtirred vp by the apprehenſion of the iniurie offered, doth more properly belong to the ſoule, and therefore I call it a mixt affection proceeding from them both.</p>
                  <p>I adde the materiall cauſe, namely the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing of the bloud about the harte, which heate or inflamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is cauſed by the apprehenſion of the iniurie offered or the diſlike which the heart co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiueth of the iniury aprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: which is either in truth an iniurie, or but in opinion &amp; appearance onely: for anger hath not alwaies a true cauſe, but ſomtime fained
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10356:8"/> and imaginary: and this materiall cauſe (namely the heating of the bloud by apprehenſion of the iniury) the formall cauſe followeth, that is to ſay, an appetite or deſire of reuenge, for before we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to reuenge the iniury, we firſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and feele it, which deſire is either iuſt or vniuſt: iuſt, if we be angry for a iuſt cauſe, with thoſe with whome wee ought to be angry, after a iuſt maner, obſeruing a fit time, and to a good end: vniuſt, if theſe circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances be not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Furthermore in this definition the cauſe of anger is expreſſed namely iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie offered (for anger alwayes preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth iniury) and the ſubiect therof which is the hart, as alſo the obiect to wit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of the iniury.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the generall definition <note place="margin">The kindes of anger.</note> of anger: now we are to ſhew the diuers ſorts thereof, or rather the diuers accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the ſame affection.</p>
                  <p>Firſt it is taken for the naturall affection <note place="margin">Naturall anger.</note> of anger as it was created of God, and had his being in man before the fall.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10356:9"/>
                  <p> Secondly, as it is corrupted ſince the <note place="margin">Corrupt anger</note> fall by originall ſinne. Thirdly as it is renewed and ſanctified by Gods <note place="margin">Sanctified anger.</note> ſpirite. Wee are not therefore with the Stoikes to confound theſe three together, and without difference to <note place="margin">The Stoicks confuted.</note> condemne them all: for how ſoeuer this affection as it is corrupted, is moſt turbulent, and of all others moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, yet we are to hould that the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affection conſidered, either as it was created by God, or ſo farre forth as it is renewed and ſanctified by Gods ſpirit is iuſt, holie, and lawfull.</p>
                  <p>And this may eaſilie be prooued by diuers reaſons: Firſt becauſe it was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">That the affection of anger is in it owne nature lawfull.</note> by God, and was in man before the fall, and before any euill entered into the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being therefore the Lords owne workmanſhip, which by his owne teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie was approoued to be very good. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 31. and of greater antiquitie then <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 31</note> euill it ſelfe, it followeth, that the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it owne nature is to be eſteemed as good and lawfull.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, becauſe in many places of <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 18</note> the ſcriptures it is attributed to God himſelfe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>the Anger of God is</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10356:9"/> 
                     <hi>made manifeſt from heauen agaynſt all impietie</hi> Ioh: 3. 36. <hi>he that beleeueth not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 36.</note> 
                     <hi>in the ſonne ſhall not ſee life, but the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God ſhal abide vpon him.</hi> Seeing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is aſcribed vnto God, to whoſe moſt perfect and iuſt nature nothing agreeth but that which is iuſt and holy, it followeth that this affection it ſelfe is ſo to be eſteemed. True it is that neither this nor any other affection is in God if we ſpeake properly, but onely attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him, that our weake capacities may better conceine how he excerciſeth his workes &amp; eternall counſailes toward his creatures: But yet for aſmuch as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is attributed <hi>&amp;</hi> aſcribed vnto him which is not good and iuſt, ſo farforth as it is aſcribed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it euidently ſheweth that anger in it owne nature is not euill.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly this manifeſtly appeareth in that this affection was truly and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie in our ſauiour Chriſt himſelfe as he was man as it is euident <hi>Mar:</hi> 3. 5. where it is ſaid that he looked angerly <note place="margin">Mar. 3. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> vpon the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes</hi> mourning for the hardneſſe of their harts: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe being incited with an holy anger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſee his fathers houſe turned into a
<pb facs="tcp:10356:10"/> market, he driueth the buyers <hi>&amp;</hi> ſellers out of the temple, <hi>John.</hi> 2. 17. ſeeing then Chriſt was angry and yet free from all <note place="margin">Iohn. 2. 17</note> ſinne, it followeth that Anger in it owne <note place="margin">Pet. 2. 22</note> nature is iuſt and holy. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on </seg>1</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it may be obiected that Anger is in many places of the ſcriptures condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 22</note> and forbidden: as <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>He that is angry with his brother vnaduiſedly is culpable of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> I anſwer that not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſimply but vnaduiſed Anger is there comdemned: <hi>&amp;</hi> in a worde al other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> where this affection is forbidden, are to be vnderſtood not of the affection it ſelfe as it was created or is renewed by Gods ſpirit, but as it is corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praued with originall ſinne: for Anger being ſactified, is not only iuſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but alſo commendable, profitable <hi>&amp;</hi> very neceſſarie, as being the whetſtone of true fortitude, whereby we are ſtirred vp and incouraged to maintayne the glorie of God, and our owne perſons and ſtates agaynſt the impietie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice of men. Though Anger therfore be but a bad miſtres to command, yet is is a good ſeruant to obey: though it be but an ill captaine to lead our forces into
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10356:10"/> the field againſt our ſpiritual and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall enemies, yet it is a good ſoldiour ſo long as it ſubiecteth it ſelf to the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and diſcipline of ſanctified reaſon. But it is further obiected by the <hi>Stoikes</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on </seg>2</label> that anger is a perturbation of the minde and therefore euill. To this I anſwere <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> that as the perturbation of the minde which is moued vppon vniuſt cauſes is alſo vniuſt and euill, ſo that which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon iuſt <hi>&amp;</hi> neceſſarie occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is iuſt and commendable: as for example when a man ſeeeth God diſhonoured, religion diſgraced, wickedneſſe vnpuniſhed; If therefore his minde be perturbed and troubled, this perturbation is not to be condemned, nay to be commended, and they rather to be condemned who are not ſo troubled. Thus was our ſauiour perturbed when he ſaw Gods houſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured, as alſo when he rayſed vp <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 2. 17 and 11. 23 No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 24. 7.</note> thus was <hi>Phinees</hi> diſturbed and troubled in minde when he ſawe that ſhameleſſe ſinne of <hi>Zimry</hi> and <hi>Cozby: &amp;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">King. 19</note> 
                     <hi>Elias</hi> when religion was conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie erected, and the Lords true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets deſtroyed.</p>
                  <p>Thogh therfore anger be a perturbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the minde it doth not follow that it is euil
<pb facs="tcp:10356:11"/> for not the perturbation it ſelfe but the cauſe thereof maketh it good if it be good, &amp; euill if it be euill. Furthermore <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">obiecti∣on. </seg>3</label> whereas they obiect that Anger blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and confoundeth reaſon, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> firſt that if Anger be temperate <hi>&amp;</hi> moderate it doth ſeruiceablely waite vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſon, and not imperiouſly ouer rule it: and rather maketh a man more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant &amp; reſolute in walking the path of truth which he hath deſcried with the eie of a cleare iudgement, then any waies dazell or offend the ſight whereby he ſhould be cauſed to ſtumble in the way, or els turne aſide into by paths of error. Secondly though it ſhould be granted that for the inſtant reaſon is ſome what diſturbed with the paſsion, it doth not follow that it is euil or vnprofitable, for before the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is inflamed, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon apprehendeth and iudgeth of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, and ſo as it were firſt kindleth the flame, which being kindled doth for the inſtant perturbe the minde, but the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation being quickly ouer paſſed and the minde quieted, reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made no leſſe fit therby to iudge of the iniury, &amp; much more fit to reuenge it. And therefore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10356:11"/> moderate and ſanctified anger is ſo farre from hurting and hindering the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it rather ſeruiceably aydeth and ſupporteth it by inciting <hi>&amp;</hi> in-couraging it couragiouſly to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that which reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath iuſtly decreed and reſolued: as therfore the moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eyſalue doth preſently after it is put into the eye dim &amp; dazell the ſight, but afterwards cauſeth it to ſee much more clearely: ſo this affection of moderate and holy Anger doth at the firſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what perturbe reaſon, but afterward it maketh it much more actiue in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and performing all good deſignes.</p>
                  <p>And ſomuch for the lawfullneſſe of Anger, both in reſpect of the firſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation thereof, and as it is renewed and ſanctifyed by Gods ſpirit, as alſo concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the diuers ſorts of Anger: Now in the next place we are to conſider which <note place="margin">What an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded and what forbidden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> of theſe is commanded or forbidden in my text.</p>
                  <p>Firſt for the affection as it was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God, howſoeuer it was iuſt and holy in it ſelfe, yet now the beauty and excellencie thereof is defaced with the foule ſpots of originall ſinne, ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:10356:12"/> there remaine onely ſome reliques of the perfection wherein it was created, till it be agayne renewed <hi>&amp;</hi> reſtored by Gods ſanctifying ſpirit. This therefore is not here commaunded or forbidden, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that we labour aſmuch as may be, that it may come neare his former excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie. The other two ſorts namely cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <hi>&amp;</hi> ſanctified Anger, the one in theſe words is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, the other forbidden.</p>
                  <p>Theſe words therefore may be diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two generall parts. The firſt an <note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> exhortation or commaundement wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in iuſt and holy anger is inioyned or commended vnto vs in the firſt words <hi>(Bee Angrie)</hi> the ſecond a prohibition or dehortation from vniuſt, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt anger in the next words <hi>(But ſinne not)</hi> and becauſe by reaſon of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption we are prone to fall into it, the apoſttle in the words following limiteth and reſtrayneth it to a ſhort time leaſt it ſhould turne into malice. <hi>Let not the Sunne go downe</hi> &amp;c. as though he ſhould ſay, though through infirmitie yee fall into raſhe and vnaduiſed Anger, yet continue not in your ſinne. <hi>Let not the Sunne go downe. On your wrath:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:10356:12"/>
                  <p> The moſt of our new interpreters think <note place="margin">That iuſt Anger is here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</note> that the firſt words are rather a permiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a precept, <hi>&amp;</hi> therfore to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtood thus. <hi>If you be angry, ſin not;</hi> or thus <hi>Are you a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gri; ſin not:</hi> that is though through infirmity ye fall into a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger yet ad not ſin vnto ſin by continuing in it. but I ſee no reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why the words ſhuld be thus wreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeeing there followeth no abſurditie or inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience, if they be playnely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood without any alteration, which cannot be avoided if we admit of their expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for I wold ask of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether is here ment a lawfull <hi>&amp;</hi> iuſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, or that which is vnlawful <hi>&amp;</hi> vniuſt: if lawful <hi>&amp;</hi> iuſt, why may it not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded ſeing it is as neceſſary <hi>&amp;</hi> profitable to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of Gods glory and our good as any other ſanctified affection; if vniuſt and vnlawfull as they vnderſtand it: I would know how we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be angery <hi>&amp;</hi> ſin not. But ſay they if a holy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger were here ment what needeth the reſtraynt, <hi>Let not the Sun &amp;c.</hi> ſeeing the longer it laſted the rather it were to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, if it were iuſt <hi>&amp;</hi> holy; I anſwer theſe words are to be referred not to the precept <hi>(Be angry)</hi> but to the prohibition <hi>(But ſinne not)</hi> where vniuſt Anger is forbidden
<pb facs="tcp:10356:13"/> as before iuſt Anger was commanded &amp; this is manifeſt in the text, for he doth not ſay, <hi>Let not the Sunne goe downe</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>vpon your Anger</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>vpon your Wrath</hi> or vniuſt and inueterate anger as this word is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vſed.</p>
                  <p>So that the ſence of theſe words is <note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the words.</note> breefely thus much: be angrie and ſpare not ſo that your anger be iuſt and holy: but ſeeing by reaſon of your infyrmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and corruption, your iuſt Anger may eaſily degenerate and become vniuſt, if due time, place, perſon, and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances be not obſerued, therefore take heede you ſin not by being vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly angry, yet if through infyrmitie yee fall in to this ſinne, do not harbour it no not one day. <hi>Let not the Sunne go downe on your wrath.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>And ſomuch for the meaning of the <note place="margin">Of iuſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> words: now I will intreate of their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts. And fyrſt concerning iuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, what it is <hi>&amp;</hi> what is required in our Anger that it may be iuſt and holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this <note place="margin">The defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of iuſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> Anger is an holy and reaſonable deſire of reuenge ſtirred vp in vs vppon iuſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10356:13"/> waightie and neceſſarie cauſes, wherby we being after a lawfull maner angry with our owne and others vices and ſins rather then with the perſons, do deſire iuſtly to puniſh and reuenge the vices &amp; ſins, to the end God may be glorified, the parties amended, and that the anger of God being pacyfied may be auerted not onely from the party offending, but alſo the church and common wealth. Firſt then it is required to holy and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Anger, that the cauſe therof be iuſt: now the iuſt cauſes of Anger are diuers. Firſt when we are moued thervnto with <note place="margin">The firſt cauſe of iuſt Anger the glory of God.</note> a zeale of Gods glorie: for when we ſee God diſhonoured, and his glory defaced it is not onely lawfull to be angry with the offendors but alſo neceſſarie: for we profeſſe our ſelues to be Gods ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, now we know that no good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect can with patience endure to heare or ſee the glory of his ſoueraigne impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: we profeſſe our ſelues Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and what good ſeruant can abide to ſee his maiſter diſgraced? we profeſſe our ſelues Gods children, and good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are more grieued and offended when they perceiue that their parents are any wayes abuſed or iniured, then if
<pb facs="tcp:10356:14"/> the iniuries were offered to themſelues: if therefore we be loyall ſubiects, fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruants, and louing children, wee cannot chooſe but be incited to a holy anger if we ſee our glorious ſoueraigne, our good maiſter, and gratious father, by any meanes diſhonoured.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſawe that the children <note place="margin">Example.</note> of <hi>Iſraell</hi> had contrarie to Gods expreſſe commaundement reſerued <hi>Manna</hi> till the next morning, he could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne himſelfe from ſhewing this holy Anger, when he ſaw his Lord and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will not obſerued, <hi>Exo.</hi> 16. 20. So that thogh <hi>Moſes</hi> were the meekeſt man <note place="margin">Ex. 16. 20. Num. 12. 3</note> that was on earth, yet could he not with patience endure, to ſee gods ordinance contemned. In like maner when he ſaw that honor and glorie which was due onely to God almightie, deriued to a baſe and brutiſh Idoll, he was prouoked to an holy anger, and ſo wholy poſſeſſed with a deuine and heauenly rage, that he not onely breaketh the two tables writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">Exo 32.</note> by Gods owne hand, but ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengeth this idolatry with the death of three thouſand of the offendors. So that though the people were dearer to him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne life, nay then the ſaluation of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10356:14"/> his owne ſoule, yet was the glory of God <note place="margin">Verſe. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> more deare and pretious vnto him then eyther of both. <hi>Phinees</hi> alſo when he ſaw God diſhonoured with that ſhameleſſe ſinne of <hi>zimry</hi> and <hi>Cozby</hi> beeing prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <note place="margin">Num. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 7. 8.</note> with an holy anger he reuenged this diſhonour vvith the death of both the offendors. Thus alſo vvas <hi>Elias</hi> zealous for Gods glory becauſe the Children of <note place="margin">1. Kings 19. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſraell</hi> had forſaken his couenant, caſt downe his alters, &amp; ſlaine his Prophets.</p>
                  <p>And thus vvas our ſauiour Chriſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed vvith a feruent zeale of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <note place="margin">Iohn. 2. 17</note> glory <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. 17. If therefore vvee vvould approue our ſelues to be Gods children, vve muſt follow their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and for as much as nothing more diſhonoureth God then ſinne, nothing ſhould Offend <hi>&amp;</hi> diſpleaſe vs more then ſin, whether it be in our ſelues or in our neighbour. When therefore vve fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne, vve are to be offended vvith our ſelues, that ſo vvee may diuert the Lords Anger from vs, for as they vvhich <note place="margin">1. Cor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. 31.</note> iudge themſelues ſhal not be iudged of the Lord, ſo they vvho are angry vvith themſelues for ſin ſhal eſcape the Lords anger. And this our anger muſt proceed to a holy reuenge. Thoſe who haue offended by ſurfeting and drunkenneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:10356:15"/> are to puniſh themſelues with faſting &amp; abſtinence. Thoſe that haue wallowed them ſelues in voluptuous pleaſures are to ſubdue and mortifie them, though they be as deare and precious vnto them as their right hand and eye. Thoſe who haue defrauded their neighbour by pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyning away his goods are with <hi>Zache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> to make reſtitution foure fold, <hi>Luke.</hi> 19. 8.</p>
                  <p>And as we are bound by the lawe of charitie to loue our neighbours as our ſelues, ſo alſo to be angry with them as with our ſelues, namely with this holy kinde of Anger for ſinne. Whenſoeuer therefore wee ſee them by their ſinnes diſhonour God we are to be diſpleaſed therewith, and ſo farre forth as the limits of our callings extende to ſhewe our ſelues offended, according to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> who becauſe the people would not heare the worde of the Lord was euen filled with diuine wrath, <hi>Jeremie.</hi> 6. 10. 11. But how colde <note place="margin">Ier. 6. 10. 11.</note> mens zeale of Gods glory is in this age fro ſen in the dregs of ſinne, too lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table experience ſheweth: for firſt who almoſt is angry with himſelf for his ſins
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10356:15"/> in this reſpect becauſe he hath by them diſhonoured God? euery one ſheweth ſpleene inough if his ſinnes receiue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment, but hauing to doe with them ſelues in reſpect of the ſinne it ſelfe they are like mild doues, without gaule. The adulterer is much diſpleaſed if for his ſin he be enioyned to maſke in a white ſheete, though thereby he haue deſerued death, but the poiſon of his ſin is moſt ſweet to his e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenomed appetite. The couetous extortioner is much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended if he be iuſtly depriued of that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which he hath vniuſtly gotten, but he is not angry with his ſin into which he is fallen, by vniuſt comming by them. The blaſphemer is enraged if he be but reproued for his blaſphemie, though by the law of God he deſerueth to die for it, but he is nothing diſpleaſed with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for diſhonouring the maieſtie of God: In a word euery one is angry with the ſmalleſt puniſhment, yet not moued with the greateſt ſinne: but if we would be angry and ſinne not, we muſt not be ſo much diſpleaſed for incurring that puniſhment which we haue iuſtly deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as that by our ſinnes we haue diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured
<pb facs="tcp:10356:16"/> God.</p>
                  <p>And the like abuſe there is of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger towards others: men are ſoone ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to choller agaynſt their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures vpon euery ſlight occaſion and ſhew of iniury offered to themeſlues though it be but an vnkind worde, or a miſtaken ſpeach, or but a ſtrange coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance: but when God is diſhonoured, his name blaſphemed, his religion deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, his Sabaoths prophaned, his whole worſhip and ſeruice contemned, they can looke vppon the offendors with a ſmiling countenance and ſo confirme them in their ſinne, or if they be angery they will either nor be ſeene in it at all, or ells they will ſhew it after ſo colde a manner, that it ſhal hardly be diſcerned. Whereas if there be the leaſt iniury of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to themſelues they can contayne their fury in nolymites, till it be ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with reuenge euen vnto bloud. But if we would approue our ſelues to be be Gods childern <hi>&amp;</hi> ſeruants vve muſt be as truly zealous of his honour <hi>&amp;</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as of our ovvne credit and reputation</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond cauſe of iuſt anger is vvhen
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10356:16"/> iniury is vniuſtly offred vnto our ſelues: for by the lavv of God vve are bound <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe of iuſt anger is iniury offered to a mans ſelf.</note> to ſeeke the preſeruation of our ovvne good name <hi>&amp;</hi> ſtate: <hi>&amp;</hi> therfore vvhen either of them is violated or impeached, vve may iuſtly vſe aide of the holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in defending our ſelus and repelling iniury, yea alſo in taking ſuch reuenge as is fit in reſpect of our callings: that is by vnſheathing the Svvord of iuſtice if it be committed into our hands, or by ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the help of the magiſtrate if our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate eſtate vvill not admit vs to be our ovvne caruers. Many examples might be brought to cleare this point if it vvere neceſſary. Though <hi>Moiſes</hi> vvere the meekeſt man liuing yet vvhen he was <note place="margin">Nom: 16. 15.</note> contumeliouſly abuſed by <hi>Corah</hi> and his companions, it is ſaid he waxed very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and prayed vnto the Lord, that he ſhuld not reſpect their offerings <hi>Nom:</hi> 16 15. thogh the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> were of more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an admirable patience yet being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly ſmitten by the commaundement of the high <hi>Prieſt</hi> he ſhevveth his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by a ſharpe reproufe. <hi>Act:</hi> 23. 2. yea our ſauiour Chriſt the lyuely e pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of true patience, vvhen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie <note place="margin">Act. 23. 2.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10356:17"/> to all iuſtice he was ſtroken by the high <hi>Preiſts</hi> ſeruant, he ſheweth himſelf diſpleaſed by his reprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though at that time he offered himſelfe as it were <note place="margin">Iohn. 18. 23.</note> to ſuffer all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelious iniuries which pride aſſiſted with malice could imagin or impoſe.</p>
                  <p>But here it may be obiected that our <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō. </seg>
                     </label> ſauiour hath taught vs if wee haue <note place="margin">Math. 5. 39.</note> receiued a blowe on the one cheeke to turne the other. I anſwer that Chriſts <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> meaning is not that we ſhould expoſe our ſelues to all iniuries, but that wee ſhould refrayne from priuate reuenge without any calling thereunto, which he would haue ſo farre from vs, that rather we ſhould be readie to receiue a new iniury then vniuſtly reuenge that which we haue receiued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>The third cauſe of iuſt anger is when iniurie is offered to our bretheren, for <note place="margin">The third cauſe of iuſt Anger is iniury offered to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour.</note> as by the law of charity we are bound to loue them as our ſelues, ſo the ſame law bindeth vs to be angry for thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries which are offered vnto them, as if
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10356:17"/> they were offered vnto our ſelues. And thus was <hi>Moſes</hi> angry with the <hi>Egyptian</hi> who wronged the <hi>Iſraelite. Act.</hi> 7. 24. <note place="margin">Act. 7. 24. 2. Sam. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</note> Thus was <hi>Dauid</hi> angry with <hi>Ammon</hi> for deflowring his ſiſter. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 21. and with <hi>Abſolon</hi> for his cruell murthering of <hi>Ammon.</hi> And thus was good <hi>Nehemie</hi> prouoked to anger whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple oppreſſed. <hi>Neh.</hi> 5. 6. And this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <note place="margin">Neh. 5. 6</note> is not onely lawfull but alſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, and the neglect thereof a greiuous ſinne in Gods ſight, as we may ſee in the example of <hi>Elie:</hi> for when his ſonnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed the Lords people and he would not for their ſinne ſhewe his anger in correcting them otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by milde and louing admonitions, his indulcencie moued the Lord to inflict vpon him a moſt heauie puniſhment, <hi>Et quia ira E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
                     <hi>tepuit in filios ira Dei exarſit in ipſum.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Elie</hi> his anger was luke warme towardes his ſonnes the anger of God waxed fire hotte agaynſt him, and that iuſtly, for as one ſayth, <hi>Non iraſci cum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet eſt nolle peccatum emendare.</hi> Not to <note place="margin">Gregorie.</note> be angrie when iuſt cauſe is offered is to nill the amendment of ſinne: and not to hinder ſinne when a man hath
<pb facs="tcp:10356:18"/> good opportunitie and a lawfull calling thereunto is to be come acceſſarie.</p>
                  <p>But as they offend agaynſt the partie who is iniured, ſo alſo agaynſt him who doth the iniurie. For by not ſhewing themſelues offended, they giue approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by geuing approbation they countenance and confirme him in his ſinne. Whereas if they ſhewed their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure it might be a notable meanes to reclayme him, by working in his hart a conſideration of his offence for which he is reproued. And in this reſpect <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayth that <hi>Anger is better then laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for by a ſad countenance the hart is made better. Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 5. <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 5.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the iuſt cauſes of anger: but there is further required to <note place="margin">The cauſe of iuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger muſt be waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> holy and lawfull anger, not onely that the cauſe be iuſt, but alſo weightie and of ſome importance; for if euery ſmal trifle be ſufficient to prouoke vs to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, well may we manifeſt great iuſtice, but without queſtion we ſhall ſhewe little loue: for loue ſuffereth long, it is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10356:18"/> not eaſily prouoked to anger, it ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 4. 5. 7. it coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 4. 5. 7. 1. Pet. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> a multitude of ſinnes, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 8. how little loue therefore haue they who are angry vppon euery ſmall and trifling occaſion how iuſt ſoeuer it be? Let vs then before we let the raynes looſe to anger, conſider not only of the iuſtneſſe of the cauſe, but alſo whether it be light or waightie; and if we finde that it is but a trifle, we are eyther wiſely to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble it or mildly to paſſe it ouer, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in many things we offend all: <note place="margin">Iam. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.</note> if waightie then we may not onely iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo neceſſarily we are bound to ſhewe our anger; for it is no leſſe a ſinne to ſhewe mildeneſſe where the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth anger, then anger where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth mildeneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the cauſes of our <note place="margin">What is re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quired to iuſt anger in reſpect of the maner. 1. Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> anger: now we are to ſpeake of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, wherein firſt this generall rule is to be obſerued, that we vſe moderation, leaſt we mingle therwith our corrupt &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10356:19"/> carnall anger, and ſo it degenerates into fleſhly anger, and from that to fury. Let vs therefore herein imitate the Lord himſelfe who in wrath remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth mercie; and not ſo be carried away with the violence of anger, that in the meane time we forget loue. And on the other ſide we are not with <hi>Ely</hi> to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together remiſſe and milde when either Gods glory or our nighbours good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that we ſhould ſhew iuſt anger, and ſo by approuing the ſinne for his ſake that offendeth make our ſelues ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the ſinne and conſequently ſubiect to the puniſhment; but we muſt keepe the meane if we will approue our Anger to be iuſt and holy.</p>
                  <p>The neglect where of cauſeth many <note place="margin">The neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deration.</note> to fall into ſinne: for ſome if they can maske their deformed anger vnder the fayre viſard of a iuſt pretence, they think they may lawfully ſhew all violence and fury in their affections: but let ſuch men know that though the cauſe of their anger be neuer ſo iuſt, yet in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they greiuiouſly ſinne agaynſt the rule of charitie; in reſpect whereof they may fitly be compared to cruell hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10356:19"/> who hauing a iuſt cauſe to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their office (namely the Iudges lawfull commaundement) do in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution thereof vſe all barbarous cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: ſo they beeing commaunded by God to be angry with the ſinnes of their bretheren, ſeeme glad they haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſuch an occaſion to ſhew their rage and fury: But howſoeuer ſuch men pretend the goodly title of iuſtice, yet if they be vnmaſked there will appeare nothing but rancour and malice diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnder this fayre pretext: for let their friend to whom they are and muſt bee much behoulden commit offences farre more notorious, and they who ſeemed almoſt choaked with a ſmall gnatte, can finde roume in their conſciences to ſwallow a pill of ſinne as bigge as a Camell, if it be ſugered ouer with the ſweete title of freindſhip. Others vnder pretence of a milde or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient nature are content to heare God diſhonoured, his ſeruants ſcorned, and all religion diſgraced; but curſed be ſuch mildeneſſe as cauſeth vs to betray the glory of God and his truth by houlding our peace and wincking at the
<pb facs="tcp:10356:20"/> offenders. Theſe men who are ſo milde &amp; modeſt in defending Gods cauſe that they are readie to bluſh if they but in a worde ſhewe their diſlike of ſinne, as though they had done that whereof they might be aſhamed, will bluſh and ſwell for anget if their owne credit bee but touched, or their reputation ſuffer any diſparagement; and whence doth this proceed but from the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much loue of themſelues, and ouer little loue of God? whence is this baſtard mildeneſſe but from pride the mother of euill, which cauſeth them to ſeeke the prayſe of humanitie and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie by betraying Gods glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond thing required in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <note place="margin">2 Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an modeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> is that vvee obſerue chriſtian mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie and charitie in abſtayning from malicious and wicked ſpeeches, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and ſpitefull actions in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our anger; and to this purpoſe we are alwayes to remember of what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10356:20"/> vvee are; for vndoubtedly how iuſt ſoeuer our cauſe be, if we defend it with ſpitefull and bitter ſpeeches it is not the ſpirit of God which ſpeaketh in vs. Let vs rather follow the example <note place="margin">Ioh. 18. 23.</note> of our ſauiour Chriſt, who when he was buffeted and groſely abuſed repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the offender vvith great milde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and of <hi>Michaell</hi> Tharchangell who vvhen he ſtroue <hi>with the Deuill himſelfe about the bodie of</hi> Moſes, <hi>durſt not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iude. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>blame him with curſed ſpeaking, but ſayd the Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</head>
                  <p>The third thing required is that in <note place="margin">3. A fit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum and due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> our anger there be obſerued a fit deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, and due reſpect, and that both in regarde of the partie himſelfe, who is prouoked to Anger, and alſo the other vvith vvhome hee is angrie; for fyrſt in reſpect of the partie himſelfe, hee is not to behaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alike in vvhat place and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:10356:21"/> ſoeuer he be: for if he be a magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate he is to ſhew his anger not onely in countenaunce and vvoorde, but alſo in action, if he be a father he is not with <hi>Elie</hi> to ſhewe his diſpleaſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his rebellious ſonnes onely by milde admonition, but alſo by diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reete correction: on the other ſide it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for him who is a priuate man if he manifeſt his anger in woord or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Nay it is vnlawfull for him to proceede any further vnleſſe his calling warrant him the revnto. Agayne the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders are not to be vſed al alike, a mean priuate man is not to ſhewe his anger in the ſame maner to a noble man or a magiſtrate as he would to his equall or inferior, for though he may iuſtly be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with his ſinne, yet he is to reuerence his place and calling. The ſonne muſt not ſhewe his anger towardes his father as the father ſheweth his towardes his ſonne, for he is bound to feare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence his perſon though he iuſtly hate his ſinne.</p>
                  <p>And both theſe pointes haue the <note place="margin">Examples</note> Saintes from time to time duly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: <hi>Moſes</hi> beeing a Magiſtrate to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10356:21"/> whom the ſworde of iuſtice was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, when he was prouoked to anger by the ſinne of the people, did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhew his anger in countenance or by a milde admonition, but by vnſheath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſworde of Iuſtice, and iuſtlie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing <note place="margin">Exod. 32. 27.</note> the offenders for their execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble idolatrie. <hi>John Baptist</hi> hauing onely authoritie to vſe the ſworde of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, being offended with the hypocriſie of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> expreſſeth his <note place="margin">Math: 3. 7.</note> anger by ſharpe and vehement repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions: <hi>Iacob</hi> beeing a priuate man <note place="margin">Gen. 31. 36.</note> ſheweth his anger towards churliſh <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> his father in lawe by milde and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle admonitions. <hi>Ionathan</hi> being iuſtlie incenſed by the barbarous tirannie of <note place="margin">1. Sam: 20 34<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> his mercileſſe father; ſignified his anger onely by riſing from the table and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting. The three children though with a godlye zeale they abhorred the <note place="margin">Dan. 3. 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> kings prophane idolatrie, yet they ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed their diſpleaſure in humble &amp; reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue words. And ſo though <hi>Paul</hi> deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the gentiliſme of <hi>Feſtus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> yet he vſed them with all due reſpect as it beſeemed their high callings. By all <note place="margin">Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 25</note> which examples it is manifeſt that we
<pb facs="tcp:10356:22"/> are to vſe Chriſtian ſeemelines and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion if we would haue our anger ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued as iuſt and holy.</p>
                  <p>And ſomuch for the manner of our <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 11.</note> Anger; in the next place we are to ſpeak <note place="margin">The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of iuſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> of the obiect thereof; and that muſt not be the perſon of our neighbour, but his vice, ſinne, and iniuſtice. For though we are to be angrie at, yea to hate the vices of men, yet we are to loue their perſons, and in the middeſt of our anger, to ſeeke their good, eſpecially the ſaluation of their ſoules, and in regard hereof we we ought to grieue more for their ſinne, then for the iniures which by their ſinnes they haue offered vs. And thus was holy <hi>Dauid</hi> affected whoſe zeale did euen conſume him, becauſe his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had forgotten the worde of the <note place="margin">Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 119. 139.</note> Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 139. and ſuch was the anger of our Sauiour Chriſt, who in the mideſt thereof did mourne for the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their harts. <hi>Mar.</hi> 3. 5. But on the <note place="margin">Mar. 3. 5.</note> other ſide we are to take heede that we doe not approue of the ſinne for the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders ſake, for we ought to hate ſinne in our friends, parents, yea in our owne harts or whereſoeuer els we finde it, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10356:22"/> in no wiſe to loue this deadly poyſon, though it be brought vnto vs in a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of gold neuer ſo precious in our eies. Here therefore we muſt avoyd two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, the one to hate the perſon for the ſinnes ſake; The other to loue the ſinne for the perſons ſake: for as we would condemne his folly who would loath an exquiſite picture becauſe it had a ſpot of dirt vpon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, or his that ſhould ſo extreamly dote vpon the rare work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of ſo excellent a feature, that he alſo would be in loue with the dirte for the pictures ſake, and on the other ſide co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend his wiſdome who ſhould ſo like the picture as in the meane time he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liketh of the deformitie; So alike fooliſhe is he who will be angrie at the perſon of man it ſelfe which was formed after Gods owne image becauſe this image is ſpotted and defiled with ſinne, or he who will like and approue of ſuch filthie corruptions and deformites where with it is defaced; but he is truly wiſe who ſo hateth the polluted ſpots of ſynne, that in the meane time he loueth Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent workemanſhip, and ſo eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of the workemanſhip, that he is
<pb facs="tcp:10356:23"/> much diſpleaſed with the pollution which deformeth it. But the practiſe of the world is farre otherwiſe: for men will hardlie be friend to the perſon, but they will be a friend to the ſinne alſo; nor an enimie to the ſinne, but they will with all maligne the perſon; or els that which is worſe, they will hate the perſon of their neighbour and loue his vice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 12.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the obiect of iuſt anger. The fourth thing to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">The tyme of iuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> in iuſt anger, is the time which muſt be ſhort. Not that it is vnlawfull to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long in anger if it continue iuſt, but leaſt our holy anger by reaſon of our corruption degenerate into malice. For as the moſt pure wine doth in time waxe ſower vpon the dregs; ſo our moſt holie anger if it be long retained, is in daunger of receauing ſome ſowreneſſe of malice from the dregs of our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. The ſaufeſt therefore and beſt courſe, is quicklie to be appeaſed, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie if the partie offending ſhew ſignes of repentance, eyther for his ſinne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10356:23"/> God, or his iniurie offered vnto vs: for ſeeing vppon hartie ſorrow God pardoneth and forgiueth, let vs not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that which he remitteth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 13.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the time: The laſt <note place="margin">The ende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in iuſt anger.</note> thing to be conſidered is the end which (if we would haue our anger iuſt and holie) muſt be iuſt and holy alſo. The end of our anger is iuſt and holy, when therein we propound vnto our ſelues eyther the glorie of God, or the publick good of the church or common wealth, or the priuate benefit of him who either ſuffereth or doth the iniure. Firſt for the glorie of God, we ſet it forth by our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <note place="margin">The glory of God.</note> either when being priuate men we ſhew our ſelues his children and ſeruants by manifeſting our hatred and deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne in word or countenance, and ſo adorne the profeſſion which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe; or being Magiſtrates doe become his inſtruments in puniſhing ſinnes, and executing iuſtice; if therfore either pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men or Magiſtrates propound vnto themſelues this maine and principall
<pb facs="tcp:10356:24"/> end in their anger it is iuſt and holie.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond end is the good of the <note place="margin">2. The good of the church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</note> church and common wealth, which end, though it appertaine vnto all which are members of theſe bodies, yet dooth it more properly belong vnto Magiſtrates, who are to ſhew their anger in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne, not onely that ciuill iuſtice vvhich is the proppe of the common vvealth may be mainteined, but alſo that Gods anger vvhich hangeth ouer whole countries vvhere ſinne is countenanced or not iuſtly puniſhed may be auerted: for if ſynne be puniſhed by men in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, God vvill not puniſh the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvealth for it. Whereas otherwiſe if Magiſtrates vvincke at ſynne, and ſo neglect their dutie impoſed by God, the Lord vvill in anger take the ſworde of Iuſtice into his owne hands, and puniſh not only the malefactour for offending, but the Magiſtrate for not executing his duty, yea the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth which is ſtained and polluted with their ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>Examples hereof are plentifull in the <note place="margin">Examples.</note> vvorde of God, for the ſynne of <hi>Zimrie</hi> vvith <hi>Cozby</hi> God ſent a greiuous plague <note place="margin">Nom. 25.</note> amongſt the people, but after <hi>Phinees</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:10356:24"/> had executed iuſtice by ſlaying both the offenders the plague ceaſed. For the ſinne of <hi>Achan</hi> God tooke away the hartes from the people, ſo that they fled and <note place="margin">Ioſ. 7.</note> ſome of them fell before the men of <hi>Ai,</hi> but vvhen the malefactour vvas iuſtlie puniſhed, Gods anger vvas appeaſed. <note place="margin">Iudge. 21.</note> Becauſe the <hi>Beniamites</hi> did not puniſh but rather countenance the ſynne of thoſe vvho ſo ſhameleſly did abuſe the <hi>Leuites</hi> concubine, vve know vvhat fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, not onely the offenders but alſo the vvhole tribe (ſome fewe excepted) vvere attached by Gods heauie iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If therefore Magiſtrates would haue the Lords anger auerted either from themſelues, or the commonwealth, they are to ſhevv their anger in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſynne: and if in drawing out the ſworde of Iuſtice againſt iniquitie, they propound vnto themſelues the good of the Church and common-vvealth, their end is iuſt and holie, and their anger alſo.</p>
                  <p>The third end of iuſt anger, is the good <note place="margin">3. The good of the party who ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the iniury.</note> of the party who ſuffreth the iniurie, for hereby the offendour is reſtrained from committing the like, when either priuate
<pb facs="tcp:10356:25"/> men ſharpelie reprooue him, or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſeuerelie puniſh him for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; whereas if neither priuate men do by their anger ſhew their diſlike, nor magiſtrates inflict puniſhment for his miſdemeanour, he is readie to redouble his iniuries.</p>
                  <p>The laſt end is the good of the party <note place="margin">4. The good of the party who offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the iniury.</note> who by offering the iniurie prouoketh vs to anger. For priuate men are to be angrie with their neighbour, not becauſe they maligne him or ſeeke his hurt, but becauſe they may diſcourage him in his ſinne and ſo worke his amendment. And in like maner Magiſtrates muſt ſhevv their anger in puniſhing offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not to reuenge themſelues on their perſons, but that they may ſeeke their good in reforming their vices For what greater good can a man doe his brother then to reclayme him from his ſinne vvhich otherwiſe vvould deſtroy both body and ſoule by remaining in it?</p>
                  <p>But heere it may be demaunded how he ſeeketh his good and amendment <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō. </seg>
                     </label> vvhen the puniſhment is capitall. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere firſt in thoſe caſes there is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> of the publick good of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10356:25"/> wealth with the priuate good of the partie offending, which is to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in reſpect of the other: if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his offence bee ſuch as deſerueth death he is to be puniſhed with death that the burthen do not lie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the land. Secondly I anſwere, he doth the partie good by bringing him to the ſight of his ſinne, and repentance by apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the paine of the puniſhment; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as otherwiſe he would deſperatly runne on in his ſinnes and ſo caſt away both bodie and ſoule. To preuent therefore and cure this deſperate diſeaſe, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to apply deſperate phyſicke and to deſtroy the bodie, that both bodie and ſoule may be ſaued.</p>
                  <p>And theſe are the things required in iuſt and holy anger, which if we obſerue our anger will be not onely lawfull but alſo neceſſarie, both for the ſetting forth of the glory of God, and alſo for the good of our ſelues and of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10356:26"/>
               <head>Of vniuſt anger. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>ANd ſo much for the firſt part of my text, wherein iuſt anger is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded: now I am to ſpeake of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt anger forbidden in the wordes following <hi>But ſinne not,</hi> that is by falling into corrupt and vniuſt anger. Which <note place="margin">Vniuſt anger con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as a great ſinne.</note> vicious affection is not onely here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned but alſo in other places of the ſcripture, as in the 31. verſe of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Let all bitterneſſe, and anger, and wrath, and euill ſpeaking, be put away from you with all maliciouſneſſe. So Col.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Put ye away all theſe things, wrath, anger, maliciouſneſſe,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in the 5. Chapter of the <hi>Gala.</hi> verſe 20. 21. it is reckoned among the <note place="margin">Cal. 5. 20. 21.</note> workes of the fleſh which who ſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſhall no inherit the kingdome of God. It is forbidden alſo in the ſixt commaundement vnder the name of murther; both becauſe it is the chiefe meanes and cauſe which mooueth men therevnto, as alſo becauſe it is the murther of the hart, and therefore mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in truth in Gods ſight, who more reſpecteth the hart then the hands, for a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10356:26"/> man may be innocent before him, though his hands haue ſlayne his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour if his hart haue not conſented thereunto, as appeareth in the old law, where Cities of refuge were appoynted for ſuch by the Lordes owne comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: but if the hart haue conſented and deſired any way to violate the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our neighbour (which vniuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger alwaies affecteth) though our hands are free from the act, vve are guiltie of murther in the ſight of God. And this our ſauiour Chriſt teacheth vs in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſixt commaundement <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>Whoſoeuer is angry with his</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 22</note> 
                     <hi>brother vnaduiſedly is culpable of iudgement.</hi> By theſe places it is euident that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is forbidden and condemned as a great ſinne, and therefore it is to be auoyded of vs as a moſt dangerous enemie to our ſoules health. Which <note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of this vice of vniuſt anger.</note> that we may performe with ſo much the more vigilant care: Let vs further conſider that this vice is generally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to all by reaſon of our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall corruption: ſo that there is none ſo young, nor any ſo olde, none ſo wiſe nor any ſo fooliſh, neyther male nor
<pb facs="tcp:10356:27"/> Female, which do not carrie this fire in their boſome: and therefore vnleſſe they quench dayly this fiery dart of Sathan with the water of Gods ſpirite, and the ſheild of fayth, they wilbe in danger of burning, <hi>for who can carie fire in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and not be burnt? Pro.</hi> 6. 27. <note place="margin">Pro: 6. 27.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>But the dangerouſnes of this affection will more euidently appeare if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the violence thereof: for there is <note place="margin">The vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of this turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Cant 8. 6.</note> ſcarce any other affection ſo ſtrong which it doth not eaſily ſubdue. Loue is ſayd to be ſtronger then death. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8. 6. and yet anger if it be once admitted eaſily ouercommeth it, for there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any loue ſo hartie and entire but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger hath ſubdued it: The father in his anger forgetteth his loue to his childe, and the childe to his father, the huſband to his wife, the wife to her huſband, and cauſeth them in ſtead of duties of loue to bring foorth the fruites of hatred: yea it maketh a man to forget the loue of himſelfe, as appeareth by thoſe men
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10356:27"/> who to ſatiſfie their anger violently thruſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into imminent dangers of death. Nay it maketh a man offer ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging violence agaynſt ſuch a friend as is more deare to him then his owne life, as it is euident in the example of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> who in his anger ſlew his freind <hi>Clitus,</hi> whom he loued ſo intirely that he needes would haue reuenged his murther, by putting himſelfe to a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full death. As therefore we cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the heate of the ſunne, when wee are neare vnto a ſcorching fire, ſo the heauenly heate of diuine loue is not felt if the furious flame of anger be kindled in our harts.</p>
                  <p>Couetouſneſſe alſo is a moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſtrong vice, which nothing almoſt can vanquiſh but death, and they who are poſſeſſed therewith do loue their riches better then their owne liues, as we may ſee in their example who beeing depriued of them murther themſelues; yea they are more deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them then the ſaluation of their owne ſoules, as may appeare by thoſe who fall into outragious ſinnes, whereby they plunge their ſoules headlong into
<pb facs="tcp:10356:28"/> hell that they may get momentarie riches; and by them alſo who deſpiſe the meanes of their ſaluation in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of a ſmall worldly trifle: and yet anger beeing once admitted doth ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come couetouſnes, as it is euident in the example of them who to ſatiſfie their furious anger by the death of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, are content to forfeit their goods though they be neuer ſo couetous; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the double hazard of their liues which they incurre, both in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate quarrell, and in ſatiſfying by deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued puniſhment publick iuſtice. The like alſo may be ſayd of them, who by anger beeing incired to reuenge are content to ſpend all their ſubſtance by proſecuting wrangling ſutes in law of little or no importance, to the end they may impoueriſh him alſo with vvhom they are offended; and ſo are content to pull the houſe vpon their owne heades, that they may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme another vnder the waighte of of the ſame rume.</p>
                  <p>Feare alſo is an affection of no ſmall force and violence; for oftentimes it compelleth men to thruſt themſelues
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10356:28"/> into imminent daungers that they may auoyde daungers, and to kill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for feare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> greater torments: and yet anger vanquiſheth feare, many tymes cauſing them who vvould trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſee anothers wound, contemne their owne death, and ſo turneth the moſt cowardly feare into moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate rage and furious reſolution.</p>
                  <p>So that other affections lead a man, but this drawes him, other intice him, but this compels him, other dazle the ſight of reaſon, but this makes it ſtarke blinde, other make vs prone vnto euill, but this caſts vs headlong euen into the gulfe of wickedneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>Conſidering therefore that this turbulent vice of vniuſt anger is in the eyes of God ſo haynous, in regarde of vs ſo generall, and in reſpect of it owne nature ſo ſtrong and violent, I purpoſe to intreate of it at large to the end vvee maye learne the
<pb facs="tcp:10356:29"/> better to preuent it, or the more eaſily to ſubdue it. And to this purpoſe I will firſt ſhewe vvhat it is, and vvhat are the cauſes and properties thereof; Secondly the kindes of it, and laſtly I will preſcribe the preſeruatiues and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines whereby we may cure this vice in our ſelues or in others.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt. Vniuſt anger is a wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and an vnreaſonable deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, <note place="margin">The defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of vniuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> ſtirred vp in vs by vniuſt cauſes, wherby we hauing no reſpect of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, nor the good of our ſelues or our brethren, are after an iniuſt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate maner, angry with them with whom we ought not to be angry.</p>
                  <p>That vniuſt anger is a deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, it is ſo euident that it needeeh no <note place="margin">Anger an vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueng.</note> proufe; for we know by dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that he who is prouoked vnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by an iniury offered in truth or in his opinion, deſireth reuenge according to the nature of the iniury receiued, or the opinion which he hath conceyued of it. If he be iniured by a ſcornfull looke he ſeeketh to reuenge it with a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynfull countenance; if by words he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengeth by words; if in deeds he deſireth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10356:29"/> to reuenge by deeds; yea oftentimes the fury of anger caſting a miſt before the ſight of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cauſeth ſmal iniuries ſeeme great, &amp; according to that falſe opinion, inciteth men to take reuenge without all proportion; For an angry looke with angry words, for angrye words with blowes, and for blowes with death, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the violence of the affection and not the qualitie of the iniurie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>Now that this deſire of reuenge is vniuſt and vnreaſonable it appeareth by that which followeth in the definition. And firſt becauſe the cauſes therof are vniuſt.</p>
                  <p>The cauſes of vniuſt anger are ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt anger 1. internall 1. ſelfloue.</note> internall or externall. The inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſes are diuers, as firſt ſelfe loue, whereby we ſo immoderately loue our ſelues that we neuer thinke of the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and indignities which we offer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or els ſuppoſe them to be none; or els lightly eſteeme of them, as not worthy the recitall; but on the other ſide it maketh men hainouſly aggrauate
<pb facs="tcp:10356:30"/> iniuries offered vnto themſelues: and ſo to make huge mountaines of ſmall mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils; it cauſeth the hart eaſilie to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the wrong, buſie in meditating of it being apprehended, eager in ſeeking reuenge after meditation; and the hand no leſſe forwarde in acting thoſe trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which the hart hath inuented. For by ſelfe loue men are induced to thinke themſelues worthie of all loue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and therefore if a ſmall iniurie be offered vnto them, they ſuppoſe that death is too ſmall a reuenge for ſo great an indignitie offered to ſuch worthie perſonages. Yea if they be not ſo much reſpected as their haughtie ambition deſireth, or if others be preferred before them, and that deſeruedlie, this is matter enough to prouoke them to furious rage, not onelye againſt them of whom they are not regarded, but them alſo who are preferred in others iudgement. And this is euident in the example of <hi>Caine,</hi> vvho becauſe God reſpected the offering of <hi>Abell</hi> more then his, was incenſed to wrath, and had his anger ſo inflamed that nothing could quenche it <note place="margin">Gen: 4.</note> but the bloud of his deare brother; and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10356:30"/> in <hi>Saule</hi> who could with no patience en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, that the praiſes of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould ſurmount his in the ſight and audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <note place="margin">1. Sam. 18. 8.</note> of the people, but was enraged with deadly anger againſt him, who for his merits deſerued to be aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
                  <p>And thus doth ſelfe loue make a man wincke at thoſe iniuries which he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth others, and to put on the ſpectacies of affection when he looketh on thoſe wronges which are offered to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whereby it commeth to paſſe that euerie ſmall iniurie ſeemeth great and prouoketh to great anger. Whereas if we thought meanelie of our ſelues and loued our neighbours as our ſelues, wee would not ſuffer our iudgement to be ſo ouer balanced vvith the weight of affection in iudging of the iniurie, nor giue the raynes to our anger in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing it with reuenge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sest.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond internall cauſe of
<pb facs="tcp:10356:31"/> vniuſt Anger is pride and arrogancie <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe of vniuſt anger pride.</note> of ſpirit, which is a fruite of ſelfe loue; for ſelfe loue it is which maketh vs haue an high opinion of our ſelues, this high opinion cauſeth arrogancie and pride, and pride cauſeth men to be more ſharp ſighted in diſcryeng wrong, and more furiouſlie inſolent in taking reuenge. The reaſon hereof is apparant: proude men being iealous of their honour and reputation, are alſo very ſuſpitious of contempt, ſo that the leaſt iniurie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh them to choller and diſdaine, becauſe they are readie to imagine that thereby they are expoſed to contempt. And this is the reaſon why proud men do more impatientlie ſuffer an iniurie offered in companie vvhere they would be reſpected becauſe they thinke it a great diſparagement to their credit and reputation. An example hereof we haue in <hi>Nebuchadnezer,</hi> who waxed pale for anger, becauſe he thought himſelfe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced <note place="margin">Dan, 3. 19</note> in the ſight of all his princes and people, by the repulſe which he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the three children who refuſed to obey his wicked commaundement. And in <hi>Haman</hi> who was ſo inraged with fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10356:31"/> becauſe <hi>Mordecay</hi> would not in the <note place="margin">Eſthe. 3. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6.</note> ſight of the people doe him that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which his proud hart deſired, that he thought his death too ſmall a reuenge for ſuch an indignitie, vnleſſe alſo for his ſake he vtterlie rooted out his whole kindled and nation. So that the leaſt ſparke of anger kindled with the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt occaſion burſteth out into a raging flame of furie if it be blowed with the winde of vaineglorie. Whereas on the other ſide he that is humble is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to anger though he be neglected, becauſe his lowlie conceit maketh him thinke that he is not worthy to be much eſteemed: nor yet though he haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued an iniurie, becauſe he is readie to thinke that he hath deſerued it, eyther by like faults committed againſt men, or more haynous ſinnes againſt God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sest.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>The third internall cauſe of vniuſt <note place="margin">The third cauſe of vniuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe</note> anger is couetouſneſſe, for this vice ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men deſire much riches, and if their hopes faile them and be not corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent to their deſyres, their vnquiet
<pb facs="tcp:10356:32"/> and turbulent thoughts are fit harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to prepare a lodging in their harts to entertaine anger. It maketh them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake great matters, which when they are not able to compaſſe, their harts are filled with vexation, and they become more way warde then children; or els if their couetous deſires carried with the wings of ambition mount not ſo high a pitche, they baſelie ſtoope euen to the moſt ſordidous pray; and finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnable to compaſſe great matters abroade, they entermeddle with euery domeſticall trifle at home; and if they ſee any thing miſcarrie through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of wife, childe or ſeruant, though it be of no value, their anger can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it ſelfe in no bounds of reaſon. So that theſe men are angrie abroade but madde at home, chollericke with euerie man which hinders or doth not further their commoditie, but outragious to their wiues, children and ſeruants, if they ſuſteine the leaſt loſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:10356:32"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
                  <p>The fourth internall cauſe of vniuſt <note place="margin">The fourth cauſe nice luxuriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> anger is nice luxuriouſneſſe, or luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſe niceneſſe; which commonly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fault of weomen, or at leaſt a womaniſh fault, is eſpeciallie to be ſeene in domeſticall matters. For if you come into the houſe of one who is nice and curious, you ſhall eaſilie perceiue how ſoone they are incited to great anger vppon little cauſe. If the decking and adorning of their houſe be not fullie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to their mindes, if their coſtly eates be not ſo daintelie cooked, that they may delight their curious-lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned taſte and cloyed appetite, if a ſpot or wrinckle be vpon their garments, or but a glaſſe broken, if their nice eares be offended with the leaſt diſpleaſing noice, though it be but by ſome chance, they are ſo enraged with anger, that the houſe will ſcarce houlde them, or at leaſt not containe their clamorous voyces. Theſe curious folkes are not onely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with iniuries, but alſo with ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and apparances, <hi>Nam vbi animum ſimul et corpus voluptates corrupère nihil</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10356:33"/> 
                     <hi>tolerabile videtur non quia dura ſed quia mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les patiuntur,</hi> for when volouptuous plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures <note place="margin">Senec. deira. lib. 2. c. 25.</note> haue corrupted both minde and bodie, nothing ſeemeth tolerable, not that the things which they ſuffer are grieuous, but becauſe they that ſuffer them are nicely effeminate. And like as they who are tormented with the goute, are angrie if a man come but towardes them, and crie out if they be but tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: So but a ſhew of iniurie moueth theſe voluptuous wantons to choller and anger, and the leaſt iniury offred in truth inciteth them to rage and furie. Wheras others who haue not their mindes effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated with this luxurious curioſitie, they can eaſelie paſſe ouer ſuch trifling imperfections, and repell anger in farre more violent aſſaults. If any thinke theſe <note place="margin">A prolep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</note> toyes too ſmall to vndergoe a publicke cenſure; I would haue ſuch know, that the leſſer the occaſion is which prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to anger, the greater is their ſynne who are ſo eaſelie prouoked, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they deſerue a ſharpe reprehenſion for that anger which is incited by euerie light and trifling cauſe, then if it vvere waightie and of ſome importance: for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10356:33"/> howſoeuer the occaſions are but ſmall, yet their ſinne is not ſmall, nay their ſinne is therefore great, ſeeing the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which moueth them thereunto is but little, eſpecially conſidering that the ſame parties who are fire-hot in theſe trifles which concerne themſelues are key <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>old in thoſe things which much concerne Gods glory and their owne ſpirituall good. For I appeale vnto their owne conſciences whether they are not prouoked vnto more violent anger for theſe trifling toyes, then when they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour God by moſt greiuous ſinne, or ſee him diſhonoured by others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if their conſciences plead guiltie, let them rather bee offended with their owne corruptions then with the Phyſition which deſireth to cure them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
                  <p>The fift internall cauſe of vniuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <note place="margin">The fift cauſe of vniuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</note> is curioſity, whereby men are tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with a vayne deſire and itching ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite to ſee and heare all things: how their friends behaue themſelues in their priuate meetings; what their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb facs="tcp:10356:34"/> do and ſay behind their backs; how their ſeruants beſtow them ſelues in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery corner; whereof it commeth to paſſe that deſiring to know all things they alſo know many things which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe them, &amp; prouoke them to anger, for which they may thanke their vaine curioſitie: for if with the wiſe man they would thinke it their glory to paſſe by infirmities. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19. 11. or follow his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 23. <hi>Giue not thine hart to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 11 Eccl. 7. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>all the woordes that men ſpeake, leaſt thou do heare thy ſeruant curſing thee;</hi> They might haue leſſe cauſe of anger, &amp; more contentation of minde. Whereas by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiue inquirie after euery rumor, and curious prying into ſmall domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faultes, they inflame their harts with great anger. for as the looking vppon a ſmall print doth more offend the ſight; then a greater becauſe we hould it nearer our eyes and more intentiuely behould it, the letters ſtanding thicke and neare together: ſo oft times it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe that theſe ſmall domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faultes beeing curiouſly pried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to do more offend and anger vs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are neere vnto vs and fall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10356:34"/> out thicke; and as it were one in the necke of another, then greater iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries offered abroade vvhich fall out more ſeldome and are not ſo much ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to our view.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
                  <p>The ſixt internall cauſe is to haue an <note place="margin">The ſixt cauſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie &amp; liſtning to tale-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. Pro. 26. 20</note> open eare to euery tale-bearer, and a credulous hart to beleeue them. <hi>Pro.</hi> 26. 20. <hi>Without wood the fire is quenched, and without a tale-bearer ſtrife ceaſeth.</hi> So that as wood is the fires fit nouriſhment, ſo is a tale-bearer fit to nouriſh anger. An example hereof we haue in <hi>Saule,</hi> who geuing a credulous eare to thoſe lying ſuggeſtions of that pickthanke <hi>Doeg</hi> was incenſed to ſuch raging anger, that the blood of the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prieſts was not ſufficient to quench the heate thereof, vnleſſe he ſpilt alſo the blood of all the <note place="margin">1 Sam. 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19.</note> inhabitants of <hi>Nob,</hi> yea of the oxen, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſheepe with more then brutiſh fury. And therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Doegs</hi> tongue. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. 4. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">Pſal. 120. 4.</note> it to coales of Iuniper (that is too
<pb facs="tcp:10356:35"/> hot burning coales) becauſe it ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inflamed <hi>Saules</hi> anger. Yea <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe geuing eare to the falſe reporte of <hi>ziba,</hi> was moued to vniuſt anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.</note> innocent <hi>Mephiboſheth;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauing experience of thoſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde euils which followed credulitie and liſtening after talebearers, he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that he will deſtroy him that priuily ſlaundereth his neighbour <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. 5. 7. <note place="margin">Pſa. 101. 5. 7.</note> And hence it is that <hi>James</hi> compareth the tounge to a fire, becauſe nothing more inflameth the hart to furious anger <hi>James.</hi> 3. 6. <note place="margin">Iam. 3. 6.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</head>
                  <p>The laſt internall cauſe of vniuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is want of meditation concerning <note place="margin">The laſt cauſe want of medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities. Iam 3. 2.</note> the common imperfections whereunto wee are all by nature ſubiect: for if we did but conſider that in many things we offend all, and that wee our ſelues haue the ſame faultes or greater then thoſe which we eſpie in others, we would not haſtely be moued to choller vppon euery trifling occaſion. But it is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adicted to anger, to imitate the <hi>Lamiae,</hi> who (as the Poets fayne) vſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10356:35"/> their eyes abroade, and put them into a box when they come home: ſo theſe are but too quickſighted abroad in ſpying the faultes of others, but ſtarke blinde at home in diſcerning their owne faultes; and though they haue a great beame in their owne eyes, yet they can eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne a ſmall mote in the eye of another. And the reaſon is becauſe they put their owne faultes into that part of the wallet which they caſt behinde their backs and therefore neuer looke vppon them, but the faultes of others into that part which hangeth before them, where into they are alwaies curiouſly prying.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The externall cauſes of</hi> vniuſt anger. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>ANd ſo much for the internall cauſes of vniuſt anger, now vve are to ſpeake of the externall; by which I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all outward occaſions vvhich are vniuſtly taken, as firſt vvhen vve are angry with our neighbour for his
<pb facs="tcp:10356:36"/> vertuous actions. For ſome there are <note place="margin">1. vertuous actions &amp; domeanor</note> whoſe malignant eyes do abhorre no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then the bright beames of vertue, eyther becauſe they thinke that the beautie of others perfection cauſeth the deformitie of their vices ſeeme more vggly; or that their degenerated natures are become like vnto ſathans who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vertue becauſe it is vertue. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample hereof wee haue in <hi>Cain</hi> whoſe <note place="margin">Examples.</note> anger was kindled agaynſt his brother becauſe he was accepted in Gods ſight as beeing more holy then himſelfe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 5.</note> 4. 5. as alſo in <hi>Saule</hi> who was incenſed agaynſt <hi>Ionathan</hi> for his vertuous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour <note place="margin">1. Sam. 20 30.</note> towards <hi>Dauid</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 30. in <hi>Aſa</hi> who was offended with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet the Ambaſſadour of the Lord, for deliuering faythfully that ambaſſage which the Lord had put in his mouth, <note place="margin">2. Chro. 16. 10</note> 2. <hi>Cro.</hi> 16. 10. In <hi>Nebuchadnezer</hi> who was inraged agaynſt the three children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they refuſed to commit Idolatrie, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 13. and in the <hi>Iewes</hi> who were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">Dan. 3. 13.</note> with wrath becauſe our ſauiour Chriſt made a true expoſition of the <note place="margin">Luke. 4. 28.</note> ſcriptures, and rightly applyed it vnto them, <hi>Luke.</hi> 4. 28. and too many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10356:36"/> vve haue in theſe dayes of ſuch as cannot with any patience indure to heare their duties taught them, and their vices publickly reproued out of Gods vvorde, or yet any priuate admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, but they are readie (like thoſe that are in a raging fit of a burning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue) to deſpight the Phyſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth to cure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that in our times he is like to incur more anger yea &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger alſo that reproueth ſinne, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that committeth ſinne, he that reprehendeth Atheiſme and prophaneneſſe, then he that liueth in them. Yea ſo deſperate is the diſeaſe of this declining age ſurfetted with ſinne, that the Phyſition may ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner incurre hurt and dammage by the fury of his patient, then the patient help and health by the ſkill of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Phyſition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>Secondly the cauſe of our anger is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, when it is only imaginarie, hauing no other ground but our owne ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition. And thus was <hi>Eliab</hi> angry with his brother <hi>Dauid</hi> becauſe he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb facs="tcp:10356:37"/> him to be proud whereas in truth his owne pride was the cauſe of his ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 28. and this is the moſt <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17 28.</note> common cauſe of anger in theſe dayes; for want of loue cauſeth men to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the actions of other; in the woorſt ſence, and vppon their falſe ſurmiſes they ground their anger. One is angry becauſe ſaluting his neighbour, he did not reſalute him, whereas perhaps he not ſee him, or at the leaſt hauing his minde otherwiſe occupied did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue him: another is offended if any in this companie is merry, thinking that he maketh himſelfe ſporte with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; another becauſe he is too ſadde imagining that it is becauſe his companie diſpleaſeth him. In a word as mens ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are innumerable, ſo alſo are the cauſes of vniuſt anger. Yea ſo prone men are to inuent cauſes where none is that oftentimes they are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re diſpleaſed becauſe they haue receiued ſmall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits not anſwerable to their expectation, or not equall to thoſe which they ſee beſtowed vppon others; and ſo they are prouoked to Anger with ſmall gifts as though they had receiued great
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10356:37"/> iniuries, but let vs be aſhamed of ſuch follie and learne to leaue it. Hath thy friend geuen more to an other then to thee? why it may be he hath deſerued more, and though he hath not, yet that which thou haſt receiued might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thee it thou wouldeſt make no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſions. <hi>Nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erit foelix quem torquebit</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Senec. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ira. lib. 3. Cap. 30.</note> 
                     <hi>foelicior,</hi> he will neuer be happie who is vexed when he ſeeth one more happie. Hath he geuen thee leſſe then thou didſt hope for? why perhaps thou dideſt hope for more then thou dideſt deſerue, or then thy friend could conuenientlye geue, but if thou wouldeſt not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull conſider rather what thou haſt receiued, then what thou haſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, before how many thou art pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, rather then how many are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly the cauſe of our anger is <note place="margin">3. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſe is light and of no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> vniuſt when we are prouoked therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by euery ſmall and triſling occaſion; becauſe hereby loue and charity is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably violated when euery ſlight cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:10356:38"/> incenſeth vs to anger: for loue ſuffereth all things: 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 7. and therefore their loue is ſmall who will ſuffer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 7.</note> Loue couereth a multitude of ſinnes. <hi>Pro.</hi> 10. 12. they therefore who <note place="margin">Pro. 10. 12</note> rather finde cauſes where they are not, then couer them where they are, doe plainly ſhew their want of loue, and their too great proneneſſe to anger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is the nature of loue to make great faultes ſeeme little, and little faults none at all: but anger maketh euery ſmall ſlip a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall offence, and euery worde of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace worthie a ſtabbe. And as when we behould the ſunne riſing thorough thick and foggie vapours, we imagine it to be of a farre greater quantitie then when the ayre is pure and cleare: ſo when the foggie miſts of anger doe ouerſhadowe reaſon, wee ſuppoſe euery fault to be greater then it would appeare, if this tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent affection were diſpelled with the liuelie heate of ardent loue.</p>
                  <p>Some are angrie of the imperfections of nature, which being not in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties power to amend ſhould rather moue compaſſion then prouoke anger. Others are angry at faultes committed at vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10356:38"/> vnwillinglie and vnwittinglye, whereas they might with as great reaſon be angry with a traueller for going out of his way, or with one who ſtumbleth in the darke, for not keeping footing or with a blind man for iuſtling or ruſhing againſt them; For as the want of bodely ſight cauſeth the one, ſo ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which is nothing els but the blindenes of the minde cauſeth the other; or with one who is ſick becauſe he is ſicke, for what is ignorance but the mindes maladie? but he whoſe hart is ſeaſoned with true wiſdome, is not eaſily prouoked with faults of ignorance, vnleſle it be wilfull or extreamly rechleſſe, conſidering that while we continue in this vale of miſery, our minds are ſhadowed with more then <hi>Cimerian</hi> darkenes. And therefore theſe ſmall trifling errours whereinto wee fall for want of knowledge, will in them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moue laughter, or at leaſt pitie, then prouoke anger. For as the vnhappy ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and ſhrewd turres of little children are excuſed becauſe they proceed from vvant of vvit; ſo ſhould the ſame excuſe ſerue for them vvho commit faults tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ignorance and ſimplicitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10356:39"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>Laſtlie our anger is vnlawfull when <note place="margin">4. when the end is vnlawfull.</note> as in our anger we propound vnto our ſelues no lawfull end; as the glorie of God, the publicke good of the Church or common wealth, or the priuate bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of our ſelues or of our neighbours: but rather priuate reuenge and ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of our tumultuous affections by the hurt or deſtruction of him with whom we are diſpleaſed. And this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be obſerued in all examples of vniuſt anger, as in <hi>Caines</hi> anger to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Abel; Saules</hi> towards <hi>Dauid; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezers</hi> towards the three children, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes</hi> towards our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>And ſo much for the cauſes of vniuſt anger; now we are to ſpeake of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the properties of vniuſt anger. Cap.</hi> 4.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt propertie of vniuſt anger, is <note place="margin">The firſt propertie, want of modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that it is immoderate; for though
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10356:39"/> our anger haue neuer ſo iuſt a cauſe, yet if it growe violent, and degenerate from anger to wrath and furie it is vniuſt, for it ſauoureth not of the ſpirit of God who is mercifull and eaſie to be intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but rather of the fleſh and the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption thereof. And therefore wrath (that is violent anger) is numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the works of the fleſh, the doers whereof ſhall not inherit the kingdome <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21. How to diſeeme immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate anger 1. by the fruites.</note> of God: <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 20. 21.</p>
                  <p>Now if we would know how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne when our anger is immoderate, it is eaſelie knowne by the fruites thereof. As firſt when it prouoketh vs to vtter wordes diſhonourable to God, either by prophane blaſpheming of his holy name; or wicked curſing and imprecations, whereby we deſire that he ſhould be the executioner of our malice; or oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious to our neighbours, as when our anger burſteth out into bitter and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſpeeches tending onelie to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. An example whereof we haue in <hi>Shemei</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 5. who reprouing <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 5.</note> for his ſinnes, vſeth ſuch gaule and bitternes, that it clearelie appeareth his anger proceeded not from the hatred of
<pb facs="tcp:10356:40"/> his ſinne, but rather of his perſon.</p>
                  <p>Secondly vvhen vve haue no regarde of any decorum or order, eyther in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> By the want of fit decoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> of our ſelues or thoſe with vvhom vvee are angry. Not in reſpect of our ſolues, as vvhen by anger vve are prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to take reuenge being but priuate men, vvhereas reuenge belongeth only to God, and to the Magiſtrate vvho is the Lords deputie, according to that <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 19. <hi>Auenge not your ſelues but giue</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>place to anger:</hi> (that is to Gods anger and reuenge) <hi>For it is written, vengeance is mine and I will repaye it ſaith the Lorde.</hi> They <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 35.</note> therefore vvho take vpon them reuenge hauing no lawfull calling therevnto, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate Gods ordinance by arrogating to themſelues one of Gods royall priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; ſo make themſelues guilty of high treaſon againſt God, as they are guilty of treaſon againſt an earthly prince, vvho intermeddle with any of their royall prerogatiues.</p>
                  <p>So alſo our anger is immoderate when vve haue no reſpect of the party vvith whom we are angrie, as when the ſonne being prouoked to anger againſt his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though it be for a iuſt cauſe, doth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10356:40"/> not vſe him vvith that reſpect and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence vvhich becommeth him, but bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth out into vndutifull and inſolent ſpeeches: quite contrarie to the example of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who being but a ſonne in lawe did not in his anger forget his dutie, but vſed all diſcretion and moderation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 36. and of <hi>Ionathan</hi> vvho though he had iuſt cauſe to be angry vvith his <note place="margin">Gen. 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6.</note> father <hi>Saule,</hi> yet he onely ſhewed it by riſing from the table and departing. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 34. and the like may be ſaid of <note place="margin">1. Sam. 20 34.</note> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> anger towards his maiſter, the ſubiects towards the Magiſtrate, and of all inferiours towards their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. For howſoeuer the law of God bindeth vs, to be angrie when iuſt cauſe is offered yet it alſo tyeth vs to modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſcretion: For it is the author of order and not confuſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond propertie of vniuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d propertye of vniuſt anger is in reſpect of the obiect</note> is in reſpect of the obiect, for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as iuſt anger oppoſeth it ſelfe onelie againſt ſinne and iniuſtice, vniuſt anger is incenſed againſt the perſon of the offendour, yea oftentimes of them who
<pb facs="tcp:10356:41"/> are innocent, nay becauſe they are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, as appeareth by thoſe examples which before I rehearſed: But if wee will be Chriſts diſciples we muſt follow his doctrine and example. His doctrine <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 44. <hi>Loue your enemies, doe good to thoſe that hate you, &amp;c. that you may be the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 44</note> 
                     <hi>ſonnes of your father which is in heauen.</hi> Where he plainely intimateth, that they are not the ſonnes of God, who doe not loue the perſons of their very enemies: we muſt follow alſo his example, who prayed for his enemies euen while hee was vppon the croſſe ſubiect to their outragious iniuries. <hi>Luke.</hi> 23. 34. which <note place="margin">Luke. 23. 34.</note> bleſſed preſident holy <hi>Stephen</hi> imitated. <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 66. <note place="margin">Acts. 7. 66</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But many are not only incenſed againſt the perſons of their enemies who are men like vnto themſelues, but alſo with bruite beaſts, which are not capable thereof, as we may ſee in the example of <hi>Balaam. Num.</hi> 24. 10. yea euen with <note place="margin">Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 24. 10</note> things vvhich want both ſence and life, and ſo was <hi>Xerxes</hi> angry with the riuers, <note place="margin">Plutarch. de cohib. wacun.</note> and ſent letters full of menacing threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to the hils. And many ſuch are ſubiect to continuall view, vvho if any
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10356:41"/> thing in their hands diſpleaſe them, will not ſticke to daſh it agaynſt the ground, though after they are fayne to take it vp againe, or to ſpoyle and breake it in peeces though afterwardes they muſt be glad to beſtow great labour in repayring that which by greater folly they haue defaced. But theſe men may fitly be compared vnto children who hauing gotten a fall beate the earth; ſo they hauing receiued ſome hurt through their owne folly or negligence, are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with thoſe things which are ruled by them as bare inſtruments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>The laſt propertie of vniuſt anger re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth the time when as it beeing long retayned becommeth hatred. And this happeneth not onely when men are prouoked vnto anger vppon waightie cauſes, but alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on the moſt ſlight occaſions: for when vayne trifles haue ſtirred them vp to wrath they perſeuer in it, leaſt they might ſeeme to haue begunne without cauſe, and ſo agaynſt all reaſon the vniuſtice of
<pb facs="tcp:10356:42"/> their anger makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perſiſt in it with greater obſtinacie. For therfore they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne it yea increaſe it, that the greatnes of their anger may make men beleeue that it could not chooſe but ariſe from ſome waightie occaſion &amp; iuſt cauſe: &amp; ſo they chuiſe rather to ſeeme iuſt then to be iuſt. But more of this afterwardes when I come to ſpeake of the reſtraynt of vniuſt anger.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the kindes of vniuſt anger.</hi> Cap. 5.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>ANd ſo much concerning the cauſes and properties of vniuſt anger, now we are to ſpeake of the kindes thereof. It admitteth of a twofould diſtinction: firſt it is eyther hidden and couert, or els profeſſed and manifeſt. Hidden anger is <note place="margin">Hidden anger which is comenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> of two ſortes; the firſt is commendable when as men labour by all meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to ſubdue the affection <hi>&amp;</hi> to ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the flame after it is kindled that it burſt not forth into vnſeemely wordes or actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſauouring of reuenge. And this is a fruite of the ſpirite, which when it cannot repell anger and keepe it from entrance; in the next place it endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10356:42"/> to expell and repreſſe it.</p>
                  <p>The other ſorte of hidden anger is to <note place="margin">Hidden anger which is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</note> be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned, when as men nouriſhing it in the hart do notwithſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale it, that they may haue the better o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, which they are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſeeke with ſuch a full reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they refuſe all parley leaſt they might be brought to a truce or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude a peace. This anger is farre worſe then that which is profeſſed both in reſpect of the partie who is angry, and the other with whom he is angry. In reſpect of the partie himſelfe becauſe contayning in him this turbulent affection, it doth vex and torment him, like a raging fire which hath no paſſage, or a violent ſtreame whoſe current is ſtopped. And hereof it is that anger is ſayd to be of the vipers brood becauſe it pineth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth him in whom it is bredde. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of him alſo with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is angry, becauſe it maketh him leſſe wary in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting his malice, <hi>&amp;</hi> therfore the more eaſily ſurpriſed. In regard whereof a ſecret enemie is more daungerous then one who profeſſeth his emnitie, for as a ſmall companie of men lying in
<pb facs="tcp:10356:43"/> an ambuſhment, will more eaſely ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a greater force, then if they ſhould march agaynſt them with banners diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played: ſo a weake enemie hiding his anger and watching his beſt oportunity of reuenge, is more like to circumuent and ſurpriſe one more mightie then himſelfe, then if he ſhould profeſſe his malice.</p>
                  <p>Examples hereof wee haue in the <note place="margin">Examples</note> ſcriptures: in the olde ſerpent who clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked extreame malice vnder goodly wordes and fayre promiſes, profeſſing himſelfe a kinde friend to our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes when hee wholy intended their eternall deſtruction. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 1.</note> in <hi>Cain</hi> who talked familiarly with his brother as in times paſt when as he alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die had reſolued his murther in his hart, which alſo preſently after he acted with his hands. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 8. So <hi>Abſolon</hi> like a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 8.</note> courtier concealed deadly malice two yeeres together againſt his brother <hi>Ammon;</hi> to the end that beeing not ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected he might obtayne the more fit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of reuenge. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 22. 23. <note place="margin">2. Sam. 13. 22. 23.</note> The like example we haue in <hi>Ioab</hi> who kindly ſaluting <hi>Amaſa</hi> cruelly ſtabbed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10356:43"/> him while he louingly embraced him. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 9. As alſo in the traytor <hi>Iudas</hi> who betrayed his mayſter while he kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">2. Sam. 20 9.</note> him. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 47. Neyther is our age fruitfull in all ſinne, barraigne of ſuch <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 47.</note> example<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: for how many Italionate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiuilians liue among vs, who will not ſticke to giue moſt kinde congeis with hand cappe and knee, to them from whom they are moſt en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nged in their harts; and looke moſt ſmoothly vppon them agaynſt whom they haue concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued deepeſt malice? So that their anger is like vnto riuers which are moſt daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly deepe where the ſtreame run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſtilleſt and ſmootheſt. If you aſke theſe men the reaſon hereof, they wil tell you that (according to the rules of their maiſter <hi>Machiuill.) Profeſſa perdunt odia</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Senec in Medea.</note> 
                     <hi>vindictae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ocum.</hi> Profeſſed anger taketh a way oportunitie of reuenge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but let vs know that as in malice, and diſſembling thereof, they are like vnto the Deuil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo without repentance they ſhall be like to him in puniſhment. And ſo much for hidden anger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>Profeſſed anger is to be ſeene when ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Profeſſed anger two fould.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10356:44"/> men of ſet purpoſe do neglect the ſignes and duties of loue, or els in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>&amp;</hi> bringing forth the fruits of a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. For the firſt: ſome in their anger are ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenly <note place="margin">1. Sullen or ſilent anger.</note> ſilent from day to day, and moneth to moneth, not vouchſaufing to ſpeak a worde to thoſe with whom they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, though they dayly conuerſe with them; as though with their loue &amp; charitie they had loſt their tongues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. But ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forget the end why God gaue them a tongue, that is, that it might be not onely an holy organe to ſing our creatours prayſe, but alſo that we might be enabled thereby to conuerſe more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly and louingly one with another; as alſo that thereby we might preſerue this loue begun by taking away all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; for as the lord hath giuen a tongue to enquire out an iniurie as alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue and reprehend the offendour, ſo he hath giuen the ſame tongue to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iuſt excuſe for the working of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It may be if thou wouldeſt come to expoſtulate the matter with thy neighbour, he would eyther iuſtly excuſe his fault, or humbly confeſſe it and deſire pardon, vvhereas now
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10356:44"/> thou makeſt him thine enemie by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying him all meanes and hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation: for what hope can he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of peace, ſeeing thou wilt not ſo much as come to a treatie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>Secondly profeſſed anger is ſhewed <note place="margin">2. Anger is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by euill ſpeaking or euil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 1. Euill ſpeaking.</note> by the manifeſt fruites thereof, and they are of two ſortes euil ſpeaking and euill doeing. By euill ſpeaking, as when men do manifeſt their anger in ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full rayling vvordes vvhich are farre vnbeſeeming not onely a Chriſtian, but alſo an honeſt infidell. This is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the one and thirtie verſe of this chapter. <hi>Let all bitterneſſe, anger, and wrath crying,</hi> (that is clamorous rayling) <hi>and euil ſpeaking be put away from you.</hi> And that vve may the rather be moued to abſtaine from this odious vice, let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that God made the tongue to be an inſtrument of his prayſe and not to diſhonour him by curſed ſpeaking. And therefore hee vvill not hould him guiltleſſe, vvhich makes this heauenly organe of his ſpirite cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
<pb facs="tcp:10356:45"/> to ſhewe forth the creators prayſe a curſed inſtrument of Sathan in reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſlaundring our neighbour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth vs: <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer (ſayth he) ſhal ſay vnto his brother Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca;</hi> (that is the leaſt worde of reproch) <hi>ſhalbe worthy to be puniſhed with a councell</hi> (that is an aſſembly or ſenate of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates) <hi>And whoſoeuer ſhall ſay foole ſhalbe puniſhed with hell fire Math.</hi> 5. 22. Let vs remember that <hi>by our wordes we ſhalbe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 22</note> 
                     <hi>iuſtified and by our wordes we ſhalbe conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned:</hi> and good reaſon, for <hi>Verba ſunt animi indices,</hi> the tongue is the harts inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, and therefore our ſauiour Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Ex abundantia cordis os loquitur.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 12. 27 34.</note> Out of the abundance of the hart the mouth ſpeaketh. yea this the wiſe <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> well knew; and therfore when a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne father had ſent his ſonne to him, to the end that ſeeing him he might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſayd to the young man: <hi>Loquere adoleſcens, vt te videam</hi> ſpeake young man that I may ſee thee, noting therby that the diſpoſition of his hart was beſt knowen by the wordes of the mouth. Seeing therfore God iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth according to the hart, and ſeeing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10356:45"/> the hart is beſt diſcerned by the tongue great reaſon it is that by our words wee ſhould be iuſtified or condemned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let vs remember alſo that <hi>if for euery idle</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 36.</note> 
                     <hi>worde we muſt geue an accoumpt at the day of Judgement,</hi> how much more for rayling and reuiling ſpeaches? and if theſe meditations alwayes runne in our mindes we will in our greateſt Anger followe the practize of the Prophet <hi>Dauid, Pſa.</hi> 39. 1. that is, we will bridle our mouthes that we may not ſinne with our <note place="margin">Pſa. 39. 1.</note> tongue.</p>
                  <p>Secondly profeſſed anger is expreſſed <note place="margin">2. Euill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> by euill doeing, when either in our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger we offer imuries or ſeek reuenge for thoſe which are offered vs; both which are forbidden in the word of God. The firſt <hi>Leuit:</hi> 19. 13. Thou ſhall not doe thy neighbour wrong and <hi>Pſa.</hi> 15. 3. it is ſet <note place="margin">Leuit. 19. Pſa. 15. 3.</note> downe for a note of an inheritour of Gods kingdome not to doe euill to our neighbour: and conſequently he that is prouoked by anger to offer iniury to his brother, can haue no aſſurance with out repentance that he is an heire of Gods kingdome. And this may <note place="margin">Math. 5. 22.</note> further appeare <hi>Math:</hi> 5. 22. for if hee
<pb facs="tcp:10356:46"/> who vſeth reproachfull wordes bee in daunger of hell fire, what ſhall wee thinke of him that goeth further, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to wicked deedes? as therefore wee tender our ſoules ſaluation, let vs rule our hands though wee cannot rule our affections.</p>
                  <p>Secondly it is expreſſed by reueng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iniuries receaued, vvhich though it be not altogeather ſo great a ſinne as the other, yet it is alſo condemned and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden as no ſmall ſinne in the worde of God. <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 39. <hi>Reſiſt not euill but to him</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 5. 39.</note> 
                     <hi>who ſmiteth thee on the right cheeke, turne the left alſo. &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 12. 19. <hi>Auenge not your ſelues, for it is written, vengeance is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>mine, and I will repay ſaith the Lord.</hi> And ſo much for the firſt diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of anger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>Secondly anger is diſtinguiſhed into three kindes in reſpect of the ſubiect <note place="margin">A ſecond diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of anger in reſpect of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</note> thereof: The firſt is of thoſe who are ſoone angrie and ſoone pleaſed. The ſecond of them who are ſlowe to anger and alſo ſlowe in beeing reconciled. The third of thoſe who are ſoone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10356:46"/> to anger, and alſo long continue in it.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt they may not vnfitly be <note place="margin">1. Haſty anger.</note> compared to flax which is ſoone kindled &amp; ſet on fire, but ſoone alſo extinguiſhed vnleſſe the flame be continually nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with new matter: ſo their anger is eaſily inflamed by the leaſt ſparke of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, but ſoone mitigated vnleſſe it be nouriſhed with new prouocations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or their anger may be likened vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in thornes which maketh a great blaze for the time, and yeeldeth a crackling noyſe but ſoone goeth out vnleſſe a new ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie of matter be continually added: ſo they are ſoone inflamed, but when their anger hath a little ſpent it ſelf in wordes like the crackling of thornes, it is ſoone quenched and pacified.</p>
                  <p>Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world are ſaid to haue <note place="margin">Haſty na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> the beſt natures, but intruth it is farre otherwiſe. For that nature is beſt which moſt reſembleth God himſelfe, who as he is ſlowe to anger ſo he is ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 103. 8. 9. If therfore we would <note place="margin">Pſa. 103. 8. 9.</note> in truth haue good natures we muſt imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Lord, that is, bee long before wee are prouoked to Anger and readie
<pb facs="tcp:10356:47"/> to be reconciled; to the firſt we are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted <hi>Iam:</hi> 1. 19. <hi>Be ſlow to wratb;</hi> to the <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 19.</note> latter, <hi>Math:</hi> 5. 25. <hi>Agree with thine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie quicklie,</hi> and that not onely when <note place="margin">Math. 5. 25.</note> thou haſt offended him, but alſo when he hath offered the iniurie vnto thee and that not once or twiſe or till ſeauen times, but vnto ſeuentie times ſeauen times, as our Sauiour exhorteth <hi>Math.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 18. 22.</note> 18. 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p>But leaſt we ſhould content our ſelues <note place="margin">Haſty an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger forbid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den.</note> with this nature which of naturall men is thought commendable, let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der firſt that it is condemned and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the word of God. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 11. be <note place="margin">Eccle. 7. 11</note> thou not of an haſtie ſpirit to be angry, for anger reſteth in the boſom of fooles. Yea our Sauiour condemneth it as mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Gods ſight. <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 22. <note place="margin">Math. 5. 22.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly we are to conſider, that this haſtines to anger is a fooliſh vice, for as <note place="margin">Haſtineſſe to Anger a fooliſh and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous vice.</note> it alwayes beginneth with raſhneſſe, ſo it moſt commonly endeth with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; for after the haſtie man hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured his neighbour by vnaduiſed words
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10356:47"/> or iniurious deeds, then he ſheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſorie for it; and ſo like a fooliſh Surgeon firſt he breaketh his head and after giues him a plaiſter, which though it heale the wound, yet oftentimes it leaues a ſcarre.</p>
                  <p>And yet I ſpeake of the leaſt euils which accompany raſh anger, for how many haue there been who in their furie haue reuealed their friends ſecrets, more deere vnto them then their owne liues? yea how many thorough this raſhe anger haue violated the perſons, nay murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them with whom they were linked in the ſtraighteſt bond of friendſhip? &amp; ſo haue done that in a moment which they haue with bitternes repented the whole courſe of their liues, then the which no greater follie can be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And therefore it is well ſaid of the wiſe man, <hi>Pro.</hi> 14. 17. <hi>He that is haſtie to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>anger committeth follie,</hi> and verſe 29. <hi>Hee that is ſlow to anger is of great wiſdome, but</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">verſ. 29</note> 
                     <hi>be that is of an haſtie minde exalteth follie.</hi> And leaſt we ſhould thinke that he ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome thus offendeth, he telleth vs. <hi>Pro.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 22.</note> 29. 22. that <hi>a furious man aboundeth in tranſgreſsion.</hi> Pro. 12. 16. Eccl. 7. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10356:48"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>But here the chollerick ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil alleadge for himſelfe, that he is haſtie by nature <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                     </label> and therefore to be borne with. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                     </label> that wee haue not this nature by creation, for we were created according to Gods owne image, who is ſlowe to anger; but this corruption hath taken hould of vs by reaſon of our originall ſinne; and therfore we are not to excuſe one ſinne by another, but rather earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to labour that this pollution may be waſhed away with the water of Gods ſpirit, who by his grace doth reforme nature. For thoſe who are regenerate by the holy Ghoſt, though naturallie they be as rauenous and cruell as the Woolfe and Leopard, they ſhalbe made as milde and innocent as the Lambe and Kid: and though they be as fierce and furious as the Lion or Beare, they ſhall become as tame and gentle as the Cowe or Calfe, according to the Prophecie, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11. 6. 7. <note place="margin">Eſay. 11. 6. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>The Woolfe ſhall lye with the Lambe, and the Leopard ſhall lye with the Kid; and the Calfe and the Lyon &amp; the fatte beaſt togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:10356:48"/> 
                     <hi>and a little childe ſhall leade them, and the Beare ſhall feede with the Cowe and their young ones ſhall lye togeather:</hi> not that regeneration doth take away nature and the affections, but becauſe it doth part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſubdue their violence and furie, and partly ſanctifieth and reformeth them; ſo that whereas they were hurtfull and and pernicious, now they are good and profitable to themſelues and others, the qualitye and the obiect of them bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altered. Their loue which vvas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderately ſet on the world and the pleaſures of the fleſh, is now fixed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon God, their neighbour, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things. Their ambitious hope vvhich expected nothing but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and riches now longeth after the preſence of God and fullneſſe of ioy in the heauenly Ieruſalem. Their timorous feare wherby they were reſtrained from doing good, and conſtrained to do that which was euill, becauſe they would not diſpleaſe men; is now a notable bridle to curbe in their vnlavvfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and a ſharpe ſpurre to prick them forvvarde in the courſe of Godlyneſſe, becauſe they would
<pb facs="tcp:10356:49"/> not offend God; and whereas before it was a corrupt fountaine from which nothing did ſpring but polluted ſtreams of ſinne, whoſe deſcent is into the deepe gulph of eternall perdition, now it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>Welſpring of life to make vs auoide the ſnares of death,</hi> as it is, <hi>Pro.</hi> 14, 27. So <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 27.</note> likewiſe raſhe and vnbrideled anger, which before regeneration cauſed men to rage againſt the perſon of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, doth now oppoſe it ſelfe againſt ſinne and vniuſtice onely, whereby God is diſhonoured and the church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth damnified.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
                  <p>Do not therefore hereafter excuſe thy furious and raſhe anger by alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy nature, for thou mighteſt as well ſay, I cannot abſtaine from it, becauſe I am carnall and vnregenerate, as becauſe I am haſtie by nature: for thoſe who haue laide aſide the olde man, and are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by Gods ſpirit, haue this affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on partly tamed and ſubdued, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſanctified, reformed, and made fit for neceſſary and profitable vſes: whereas on
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:10356:49"/> the other ſide they that let the raynes looſe to this corrupt affection were neuer waſhed with the water of Gods ſpirit, and conſequently while they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in this ſtate cannot enter into the kingdome of Heauen <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
                  <p>But that we may neuer alleadge this <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 5.</note> vaine excuſe let vs conſider further that it is no better then Lazers ragges to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the deepe feſtred ſores of our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or then <hi>Adams</hi> fig leaues to hide the nakedneſſe of ſinne, which may be as fit a vizour to diſguiſe euen the moſt vgly vices as this of anger: for nature corrupted prouoketh not onely to raſh anger, but alſo to all outrages. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the murtherer by as great ſhewe of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might excuſe his murther becauſe he is by nature cruell; or the adulterer his adultery becauſe he is by nature le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous; or the theeſe his theft be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is by nature couetous, as the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his anger becauſe he is by nature chollericke. As therefore if a muttherer or theefe ſhould come before a iudge, and excuſe his fact by ſaying it was his nature, and therefore he could not chooſe but commit it, the Iudge would
<pb facs="tcp:10356:50"/> anſwere that it was his deſtinie alſo that hee ſhould bee hanged: ſo when vve ſhalbe arraigned before the Lord chiefe iuſtice of heauen and earth, the alleadging of our corrupted nature will be ſo farre from excuſing vs, that it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone wilbe ſufficient to condemne vs. And ſo much for the firſt ſort of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which is to be ſeene in angry and chollericke men.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond ſort is of ſuch as are <note place="margin">2. Anger which is ſlowly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained but long retayned.</note> ſlow to anger, but beeing incenſed are hardly pacified. And theſe are like vnto more ſolid timber, which is long before it be kindled, but beeing kindled conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth long in burning. As theſe are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the other in reſpect of their ſlownes to wrath, ſo they are farre worſe becauſe they continue in it; for anger retayned becommeth hatred, which is an affection farre more pernitious then anger it ſelfe, and much more incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible; for as raſh anger is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10356:50"/> ioyned with repentance, ſo this inueterate anger is alwayes ioyned with perſeuerance in euill. And he that is ſubiect thereunto doth not onely fall into ſinne, but alſo is reſolued to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; yea he taketh delight therein oft times by meditating on reuenge; as we may ſee in <hi>Eſau</hi> who was reſolued to retayne his anger agaynſt <hi>Iacob</hi> till his fathers death, and in the meane time comforted himſelfe by thinking on re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. 41. 42. <note place="margin">Gen. 27. 41. 42.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if we would be the children of our heauenly father; vve muſt reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him not onely in ſlowneſſe to anger but alſo in ſwiftneſſe to forgeue: and thoughour brother offend vs ſeauentie times ſeauen times, yet muſt we conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually be readie to imbrace reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 22. and ſo we ſhall not be <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 18. 22.</note> 
                     <hi>of euill, but ouercome euill with goodneſſe,</hi> as the Apoſtle exhorteth vs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 21. Whereas if we continue in malice we ſhall make our ſelues like <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 21.</note> vnto Sathan, and ſubiect to Gods wrath: <hi>For vvith vvhat meaſure we mete it ſball bee meaſured vnto vs agayne. Math.</hi> 7. 2. <note place="margin">Math. 7. 2</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10356:51"/> And as we forgeue men their treſpaſſes, ſo will our heauenly father forgeue vs. <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 14. 15. and ſo much for the <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 14 15.</note> ſecond ſorte.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
                  <p>The third ſorte is of them who are <note place="margin">Haſtineſſe to anger &amp; ſlownes to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation.</note> eaſily prouoked vnto anger, and beeing prouoked wil neuer be reconciled. Theſe men are monſters in nature, and flat op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Lord: for whereas he is ſlowe to anger and readie to forgeue, they are moſt ſlow to forgeue and moſt prone to anger. This anger I know not how to expreſſe, nor to what I may compare it, ſeeing naturall things cannot reſemble it, becauſe it is monſtrous and agaynſt the nature of all things ſauing man. For the moſt fierce <hi>Lions</hi> &amp; cruel <hi>Tigers</hi> haue ſome cauſe which incenſeth them to anger, and ſome meaſure and end of their fury after it is prouoked: and therefore they are farre worſe who are angry without a cauſe and know not how to make an end. Seeing therefore naturall things are not fit to reſemble
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10356:51"/> them, let vs conſider artificiall. they are like vnto tinder, which beeing kindled with the leaſt ſparke will alſo retayne the fire till it be conſumed: but herein they are vnlike; the tinder may eaſily be extinguiſhed but their anger can by no meanes be mittigated, the tinder doth but conſume it ſelfe, or at the leaſt thoſe things which are neare about it, but thoſe that are from them furtheſt diſtant are often ſcorched vvith the burning heate of their furious paſſion. It is like vnto vvild fire vvhich moſt eaſily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hould of euery thing and is moſt hardly quenched, but herein it is farre more violent and pernitious, that whereas wild fire may be exſtinguiſhed vvith Vinegere or Milke, this can be quenched onely with bloud yea vvith the heart bloud. There is nothing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the world naturall or artificiall, vvhich doth ſufficiently expreſſe this vilde affection; it onely can be reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by the malice of Sathan, who for no cauſe maligned God and vs, and yet his malice will neuer haue end, vnleſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we would be worſe then all things naturall or artificiall, yea as bad as the
<pb facs="tcp:10356:52"/> diuell himſelfe, we muſt be eyther ſlow to anger or readie to forgeue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The manifould and great euils which</hi> accompanie vniuſt anger. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd ſo much for the kindes of Anger: now we are to ſet downe the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiues whereby we may be preſerued from this ſickneſſe of the ſoule, and ſome medicines to cure vs vvhen vvee are fallen into it. But for as much as it is in vayne to preſcribe phyſicke vnleſſe the patient will take it; and ſeeing few or none are willing to take phyſicke vnleſſe they ſee the neceſſitie therof in reſpect of the daungerouſneſſe of their diſeaſe; I will firſt ſhewe the greatneſſe and malignitie of this ſickneſſe of the minde vniuſt anger, and afterwards pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the remedies.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:10356:52"/>
                  <p> The greatneſſe and daungerouſneſſe <note place="margin">The daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſnes of anger ſhewed by the euils which it worketh.</note> of this diſeaſe appeateth by thoſe great euils which it worketh, and that both priuate and publique. The priuate euils concerne eyther our ſelues or our neighbours. The euils which concerne our ſelues are incident to the whole man or to his ſeuerall partes the body and the ſoule.</p>
                  <p>The euils which anger bringeth to <note place="margin">The euils which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the whole man. 1 Vniuſt anger defa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceth Gods image. It ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth pietie.</note> the whole man are diuers. Firſt it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faceth in vs the image of God; for vvhereas the image of God doth ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſiſt in the vertues and graces of the minde, anger ouerthroweth them all, and firſt of all pietie which is the cheife of all, and the ſome of the firſt table.</p>
                  <p>It extinguiſheth the loue of God: for how ſhould we loue God whom vve haue not ſeene, if we doe not loue our neighbour whom wee haue ſeene? 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 20. And how doe we loue <note place="margin">Ioh. 4. 20</note> our neighbour, if vppon no cauſe or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery trifling cauſe, we be incenſed to iniuſt anger agaynſt him?</p>
                  <p>It ouerthroweth the principall part of Gods worſhip inuocation: for if we
<pb facs="tcp:10356:53"/> would <hi>compaeſſe the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lter</hi> and there of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp the ſacrifice of prayer and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing; We muſt <hi>firſt waſh our hands in innocencie Pſal.</hi> 26. 6. And this the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> requireth 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8. <hi>That we lift</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 26. 6. 1. Tim. 2. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>vp pure hands without anger.</hi> And our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt commaundeth that before we offer any gift vnto the Lord we firſt ſeeke to be reconciled. <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 23. <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 23</note> ſo long therefore as we continue in our anger we are vnfit to pray, as it moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeareth in the fift petition, where we deſire ſo to be forgeuen as we forgeue: and becauſe the Lord would haue vs deeply conſider thereof, hee thinketh it not ſufficient to ſet it downe in the Lords prayer. <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 12. but he againe doth ſingle this out of all other the petitions, &amp; inculcates it the ſecond time, verſes 14. 15. <hi>If you forgeue men their treſpaſſes, your heauenly father will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo forgeue you, but if you will not forgeue men</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 6. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>their treſpaſſes no more w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll your father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue your treſpaſſes.</hi> If therefore vvee <note place="margin">v. 14. 15.</note> offer vp this prayer vnto God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in our Anger, vvhat doe wee els but intreate the Lord that he will continue his anger towards vs? A
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10356:53"/> notable place to this purpoſe we haue. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 28. 1. <hi>He that ſeeketh vengeance ſhall finde vengeance of the Lorde, and he will</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 28. 12. &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>ſurelie keepe his ſinnes.</hi> 2. <hi>Forgiue thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the hurt that he hath done to thee, ſo ſhall thy ſinnes be forgiuen thee alſo when thou prayeſt.</hi> 3. <hi>Should a man beare hatred againſt man &amp; deſire forgiuenes of the Lord?</hi> 4. <hi>he wil ſhew no mercie to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who is like him ſelfe and will he aske forgiueneſſe of his owne ſinnes?</hi> 5. <hi>If he that is but fleſh, nouriſh hatred (and aske pardon of God) who wil intreate for his ſinnes?</hi> 6. <hi>Remember the end and let em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie paſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It alſo maketh men notablie ſinne againſt the third commaundement, by cauſing them thorough impatience to fall into curſing and imprecations, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and blaſpheming the name of God.</p>
                  <p>It cauſeth them alſo grieuouſlie to ſinne againſt the fourth commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by making them vnfit for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of the Sabaoth, as Inuocation and hearing of the worde, becauſe they who are poſſeſſed therwith haue their minds diſturbed and diſtracted either by think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon the iniurie, or els of reuenge. So that there is not one commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:10356:54"/> of the firſt table which anger doth not notoriouſlie violate.</p>
                  <p>But as it ouerthroweth the vertues <note place="margin">It ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth Iuſtice &amp; charitie.</note> of the firſt table which reſpect pietie, ſo alſo of the ſecond table which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect Iuſtice, and firſt of all iuſtice it ſelfe; whoſe generall rule is this, <hi>Vt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cuique tribuatur,</hi> that that be giuen to euerie one which belongeth to him. For anger maketh men not onelie to neglect all good duties which they owe vnto their neighbours, but alſo to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them with vndeſerued iniuries and vniuſt reuenge.</p>
                  <p>It ouerthroweth alſo charity which is the ſome of the ſecond table, whoſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule is this, <hi>That we loue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as our ſelues:</hi> for anger in ſteed of performing any duties of loue, cauſeth men to bring forth the fruits of hatred: and in ſtead of louing their neighbours as themſelues, it maketh them to hate them as their mortall enimies.</p>
                  <p>Infinite it were to ſtand vpon particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, but by this which hath beene ſaid it is apparant, that the furious flame of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger doth conſume in vs all the vertues and ſanctifying graces of Gods ſpirit,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10356:54"/> wherein principallie the Image of God conſiſteth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>Secondlie as it defaceth in vs the image of God, ſo it doth make vs like <note place="margin">1. Vniuſt anger ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men like the deuill.</note> vnto Sathan, for hee is the ſpirit of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, wrath and reuenge, as God is a ſpirit of loue and peace. It is the nature of Sathan to delight in rage and furie, for he is a murtherer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 44. not onely murthering <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 44</note> himſelfe, but prouoking others to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by filling their harts with wrathe and reuenge. And this the Heathens were not ignorant of; for they called theſe wicked ſpirits which are the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of anger, diſcenſion, and reuenge, furies, becauſe they filled mens mindes with furie and madneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly it maketh vs ſubiect to Gods <note place="margin">3. It mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth men ſubiect to Gods anger. Math. 6. 14. 15.</note> anger: for as we forgiue others, ſo doth God forgeue vs. <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 14. 15. If therefore wee retayne our anger to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes our brethren, God will retaine
<pb facs="tcp:10356:55"/> his anger towards vs. We know by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience, that he who is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an arbitratour or dayſman to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile neighbours, is oftentimes by the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward behauiour and obſtinate ſtiffnes of the one partie ſo offended and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, that whereas he was indifferent he is made an aduerſarie: ſo the Lorde playeth the part of an vmpire or arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, to worke reconciliation betweene brethren; But if either of them bee ſo ſtiffe and contentious that he will not be reconciled, what doth he els but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing the Lordes arbitrement and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetmination make God his enimie?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>Fourthly it expoſeth men to contempt: <note place="margin">4. Vniuſt anger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</note> for howſoeuer they are therefore angry becauſe they would not bee deſpiſed and diſregarded, yet nothing in truth doth ſooner worke contempt in the mindes not onely of ſtrangers but alſo of a mans owne children and ſeruants then vniuſt anger. For when their anger and the fruites thereof, clamorous brau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and fighting are vſuall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10356:55"/> aſwell for trifles as waightie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, men deſperately contemne both, when they haue no hope to preuent ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They therefore who deſire that theſe bitter drugs of correction ſhould haue any effectuall operation in the mindes of inferiours, for the purging away of their faults and vices, muſt vſe <note place="margin">Correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be vſed like Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke.</note> them like Phyſick, which if it be ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary will worke noe extraordinary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, becauſe it groweth familiar with our natures and therfore not fit to worke vppon them: <hi>nam medentur contraria:</hi> and hence it is that Phyſick becommeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to thoſe men in the time of greeuous ſicknes, which vppon euery trifling occaſion haue vſed it in the time of health, and made it as it were ſauce to diſgeſt their meate: ſo if we would haue the phyſick of the minde, correction and chaſtizement, to worke deſired effect, they muſt be vſed ſparingly and not for euery ſlippe and infirmity, which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in wiſdome ſhould be diſſembled as though it were not perceiued, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">The vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſcoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and brawling.</note> pardoned in hope of amendment, otherwiſe if euery toye and ſmall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight prouoke anger, and anger incite to
<pb facs="tcp:10356:56"/> ſcoulding and fighting, not onely the parties corrected are not bettered, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made more obſtinate and obdurate in their vices (for their harts like Anuils become harder with often beating) but alſo he that correcteth, doth diſfurniſh himſelfe of all fit remedies to cure more deſperate diſeaſes. For if he vſe bitter chiding and ſeuere fighting for the cure of euery trifling fault, what remedie doth he reſerue for correcting and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming haynous offences? ſurelie none. Whereby it commeth to paſſe, that infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours will not be reſtrained from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting all faults, but rather will be as eaſelie induced to commit the greateſt as the leaſt, becauſe there is no great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>But he who is wiſe and diſcreet will paſſe ouer many ſmall faults as though <note place="margin">Diſcretion required in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> he perceiued them not, both becauſe (as one ſaith) <hi>Gratiſsimum eſt genus veniae neſcire quid quiſque peccauit.</hi> It is the moſt acceptable kinde of pardon to ſeeme <note place="margin">Senec. de ira lib. 2. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3.</note> ignorant of the fault; as alſo leaſt tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing notice of euery little ſlippe, hee make the offendour ſhameleſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent in defending that as well done,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10356:56"/> which hee cannot excuſe as not done. Whereas ſo long as he thinketh his fault vnknowne, he will bee ſo fearefull of committing the like, that he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in hiding that which he hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die committed. But if he perceiue that the offendour taketh occaſion by his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance to offend often in the like kinde, then is hee to take notice of the fault by vſing milde admonition; if that will not preuaile, then more ſharpe reprehenſion; but yet in priuate, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie witneſſes of the fault maketh him leſſe aſhamed to commit the like; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as feare of open diſgrace will reſtraine him from it ſo long as he is not alreadie diſgraced. But if the offendour impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlie and obſtinately perſiſt in his vice, or that the fault at the firſt bee more notorious, then is hee to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede to chaſtizement and correction as the Surgeon to the mortifiyng of a member, when the ſoare is paſt all other cure. In dooing vvhereof hee is to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide all furious anger, and to vſe ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diſcretion, ioyning with his chaſtizement wholſome admonitions,
<pb facs="tcp:10356:57"/> conuincing the conſcience of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, by laying open the haynouſneſſe of his fault out of the worde of God; or els by ſhewing him how he hath offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt the lawe of nature or ciuill honeſtie. And hereby it will appeare to the offendour, that his puniſhment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the hatred of his ſinne and not of his perſon; and ſo it will cauſe him alſo more to hate his fault, them ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ſuperiour that correcteth him for it, or then the puniſhment it ſelfe which is deſeruedly inflicted.</p>
                  <p>If ſuperiours would vſe this milde and <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that followeth wel gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</note> ſober diſcretion, ſurelie it would better containe inferiours in obedience then furious anger. For whence is it that one mans looke is more regarded then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wordes? one mans milde admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, then anothers bitter reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? one mans diſcreet reproofe then anothers continuall brawling and figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting? ſurelie from milde and well gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diſcretion which worketh in inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours an awfull loue and ſonne like feare, which more ſtronglie conteineth them in obedience, and more forcibly reſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them from committing any fault
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10356:57"/> repugnant therevnto, then furious an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and rage, or the fruits thereof conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall chiding and fighting. For continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all anger and ſeuere puniſhment for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſmall fault, without admitting any excuſe, doth not make inferiours ſorie becauſe they haue offended, but carefull and cunning in hiding and diſſembling their faults, or ſhameleſſe and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, eyther in denying or defending them.</p>
                  <p>Againe as many ſtripes do harden the skin to indure them; ſo do they harden the hart to contemne them; and they which vſe much chiding do moue their inferiours to imagine that it is their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication and not any repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion. If lightening and thunder were as common as the ſunne ſhine, though they bee terrible in their owne nature, yet who would regarde them being ſo vſuall? and how much leſſe then the impotent brawling of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie man? They therefore who would haue their anger feared and reſpected, muſt let it like the thunder happen ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or els it will not be regarded like the thunder. When the Fox firſt ſaw the
<pb facs="tcp:10356:58"/> Lion, he trembled and quaked for feare, not daring to come neare him; when he ſawe him the ſecond time hee approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſomewat nearer, but when he ſawe him dayly, he feared not almoſt to come within the reache of his paw: ſo if thou but ſeldome ſhew thy ſelfe like a Lyon, thou wilt be feared and reſpected, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if continually thou appeare in this ſhape, euen thy moſt baſeſt vnderlings will not regarde thee. Yea if peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they ſpie the Aſſes eares vnder the Lions skinne, that is, follie in thy furie, (which are ſeldome ſeuered,) they will not ſtick to ride, and deride thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the euils which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <note place="margin">The euils which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt anger bringeth to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</note> bringeth to the whole man: now wee are to ſpeake of the euils which it bringeth to his ſeuerall parts, and firſt of his body. Whereas the body of man is excellent by nature, and farre ſurpaſſing all other earthly creatures, anger doth ſo deforme it, that it becommeth more <note place="margin">1. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth it</note> vglie and horrible then any of them. For it maketh the haire to ſtand an end,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10356:58"/> ſhewing the obdurate inflexibleneſſe of the minde. The eyes to ſtare and candle, as though with the Cockatrice they would kill with their lookes. The teeth to gnaſh like a furions Bore. The face now red, and ſoone after pale, as if either it bluſhed for ſhame of the mindes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, or enuyed others good. The tongue to ſtammer, as being not able to expreſſe the rage of the hart. The bloud ready to burſt out of the vaines, as though it were affraide to ſtay in ſo furious a body. The breſt to ſwell, as being not large enough to containe their anger, and therefore ſeeketh to eaſe it ſelfe, by ſending out hot-breathing ſighes. The hands to beate the tables and walles, which neuer offended them. The ioyntes to tremble and ſhake, as if they were afraide of the mindes furie. The feete to ſtampe the guiltleſſe earth, as though there were not room enough for it in the whole eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the aire, and therfore ſought entrance into the earth alſo. So that anger defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hayre of the head to the ſoale of the foote; how vgly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is anger it ſelf, when the effects ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are thus monſtrous in ſo beautifull
<pb facs="tcp:10356:59"/> a ſubiect? how monſtrouſlie doth it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the minde, when the ſignes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be thus horrible in the bodie?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>But as it deformeth the body, ſo it expoſeth it to infinite daungers by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking <note place="margin">2. It expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it to daungers.</note> men to enter into priuate frayes and needleſſe quarrels, with ſuch deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate reſolution, that they wholy neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect themſelues that they may hurt their enimy. Like to the Waſpe or Bee which venture their owne liues, that they may butſting thoſe that a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; ſo they, that they may ſatisfie their fury by reueng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſmall iniury are ready to receaue a greater, for they care not to defend themſelues ſo they may offend their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. Nay they are deſirous to geue wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, though it be through their owne bodies. And hence it is that ſome payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting anger haue put in either hand a ſword, as being fit to hurt another, but not to defend himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But what ſhould I ſpeake of receauing hurt by outward enemies, ſeeing the angrye man when he hath noe other
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10356:59"/> foes to hurt him, doth with his owne hands offer violence vnto himſelfe? as is euident in their example who in their rage will not ſtick to pull of the haire of their owne heads and beards, and to offer manie other furious outrages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their owne perſons. So that the wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> might well ſay, <hi>That a man of much anger ſhall ſuffer puniſhment,</hi> for if <note place="margin">Pro 19. 19.</note> no man els will, he will puniſh himſelfe, And ſo much for the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
                  <p>But anger bringeth no leſſe euils to <note place="margin">The euils which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the ſoule.</note> the ſoule. Firſt like a darke cloude it ouerſhadoweth and blindeth the light of reaſon, and for the time maketh men as though they were diſtraught of their <note place="margin">1 It blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> wits. Whereof it is that anger is called <hi>Breuis furor,</hi> a ſhort madneſſe, becauſe it differs not from madneſſe but in time. Sauing that herein it is farre worſe, in that hee vvho is poſſeſſed with mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is neceſſarilie, will he, nill he, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to that furie: but this paſſion is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into wittinglie and willinglye.
<pb facs="tcp:10356:60"/> Madneſſe is the euill of puniſhment, but anger the euill of ſinne alſo; madnes as it were thruſts reaſon from it imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all throne, but anger abuſeth reaſon by forcing it with all violence to be a ſlaue to paſſion.</p>
                  <p>And in this reſpect it may fitly bee compared vnto a cruell tyrant, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing inuaded the gouernment of the common-wealth, doth ouerthrow coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, lawe, and order, and ouer ruleth all by force and furie: ſo anger hauing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned ſoueraigntie ouer the minde, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away all iudgement, counſaile and reaſon, and ouerſwayeth all by fooliſh affection and raging paſſion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith well, that <hi>Anger reſteth</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccle. 7. 11</note> 
                     <hi>in the boſome of fooles,</hi> for either fooles it findeth them, or fooles it maketh them. The reaſon is apparant, becauſe anger maketh men raſhe and vnaduiſed in their deliberations, and ſo their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayles and deſignes prooue imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and without lyfe, lyke abortiue byrthes which are borne before theyr time.</p>
                  <p>Examples hereof we haue in <hi>Symeon</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Examples. Gen. 34. 25.</note> and <hi>Leuy,</hi> vvho like madde men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brued
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10356:60"/> their handes in the bloud of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye innocents to reuenge the iniurie of one offendour. In <hi>Saule</hi> who for an imaginarie fault of one man, put to death, man, woman and childe, in the Citie of <hi>Nob,</hi> and not ſatiſfied here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, <note place="margin">1. Sam. 22 19.</note> hee raged alſo againſt the beaſts with more then beaſtly cruelty. Yea <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> himſelfe beeing haunted with this furie, vowed the death not onely of churliſh <hi>Naball,</hi> but alſo of all his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25 13. 22.</note> familie for his fault.</p>
                  <p>You ſee then that anger peruerteth iudgement, ouerthroweth counſaile, and putteth out the eyes of reaſon, making it the ſlaue of paſſion, fitte to execute thoſe workes of darkeneſſe, in vvhich rage imployeth it. Lyke vnto the Philiſtines vvho hauing put out the eyes of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> made him to grinde <note place="margin">Iudg. 16. 21.</note> in theyr Myll, and to doe theyr drudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: So this raging paſſion hauing put out the eyes of reaſon, makes it a fit inſtrument for his owne buſineſſe, that is, in plotting and deuiſing that reuenge vvhich is pleaſing and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto it. VVhereby it euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye appeareth, that furious anger is
<pb facs="tcp:10356:61"/> a notable meanes which Sathan vſeth to worke our deſtruction. For when once by rage hee hath blinded the eye of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he can eaſelie leade vs into a gulphe of all wickedneſſe. In reſpect whereof Sathan is compared to a carion Crowe, which intending to make the carkaſſe of ſome ſeelie Lambe his greedie praye, doth firſt pick out the eyes, that it may not bee able by flight to preuent a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchiefe: ſo he indeauouring to make a praye of our bodyes and ſoules, doth firſt ſeeke to blinde reaſon, which is the eye of the ſoule, with the furie of paſſion, that ſo not hauing iudgement to diſcerne his ſleights, nor wiſdome to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide them, he may the more eaſilie lead vs into the pit of perdition. Or he may be likened to a cunning Fiſher man, who troubleth the water that the Fiſhe may not diſcrie his net: ſo Sathan blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our reaſon with this turbulent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that we ſhould not diſcerne the ſinnes which like nets he hath laide to intangle vs, before wee be fallen into them. For anger caſting a miſt of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation before the ſight of reaſon, maketh men vnable to iudge of good or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10356:61"/> euill, right or wrong; and whereas rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in it owne nature iudgeth that which is right, anger maketh that ſeeme right which it iudgeth.</p>
                  <p>If therfore we auoyde thoſe things moſt carefully which hurt the eyes, or if they be hurt vſe ſuch medicines as are fit to cure them, becauſe the eye is the light and guide of the whole bodie: with how much more attentiue care ought we auoide anger that blindeth reaſon, ſeeing it is the light and guide of the ſoule, which onely eye of humane direction beeing put out, like <hi>Poliphemus</hi> we wander in the deſartes of ſinne and wickedneſſe? if men abhorre drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (and that worthely) becauſe it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them differ from bruite beaſts one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſhape of the body; why ſhould they not for the ſame cauſe hate this vice of anger, which like a burning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue doth ſo diſtemper and diſturbe the minde, that while the fit laſteth it vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nothing but rauing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
                  <p>Secondly as anger hurteth the ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:10356:62"/> by blinding reaſon, ſo alſo it doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerate <note place="margin">2. It infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſoule with the heate of fury.</note> and vex it by inflaming it with fury; for what greater torment can be imagined then to haue the minde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted vppon the rack of rage? as ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we would account him a madde man, who with his owne hands ſhould ſet his houſe on fire and conſume it: ſo alike madde is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to be thought, who will ſet his ſoule on fire with the raging flames of anger, wherein it is not onely tormented in this life, but alſo (without repentance) in the life to come it ſhalbe tormented euerlaſtingly; becauſe vniuſt anger i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> murther in Gods ſight, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth. <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 22. and murtherers ſhal not inherite the kingdome of God, but <note place="margin">Math. 5 12.</note> haue their portion in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, which <note place="margin">Reue. 21. 8.</note> is the ſecond death. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21. 8.</p>
                  <p>Seeing therefore anger inflicteth on the ſoule the wound of ſinne, and ſinne vnleſſe it be cured with the ſoueraigne ſalue of Chriſtes merit, cauſeth death: Let vs carefully arme our ſelues agaynſt the violence of this paſſion, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully repell this fiery dart, with the ſhield of fayth. Yea let vs ſo ſtrongly curbe it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10356:62"/> in with the raines of reaſon, that no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward iniurie pricke it forward to ſeeke vniuſt reuenge. For as we would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne him of folly, who when a wrong were offered him by another, ſhould in reuenge wound his owne body: ſo more fooliſh is he to be eſteemed, who when another offereth him iniury doth in ſeeking cruel <hi>&amp;</hi> vniuſt reuenge wound his ſoule with ſinne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the euils which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <note place="margin">The euils which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to our neighbour 1. It ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth all friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> bringeth to a mans ſelfe: now vve are to intreat of the euils which it bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to our neighbour. Firſt it ouerthow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that excellent and comfortable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to mankinde true friendſhip; for there was neuer any friendſhip ſo inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable, which anger (if it were admitted) hath not violated. And hence it is that wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> counſaileth vs not to make friendſhip with an angry man, becauſe he wilbe ſure to breake it. <hi>Pro.</hi> 22. 24. wel <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 24</note> therefore may that ſpeach of <hi>Juno to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecto</hi> be applyed to anger.</p>
                  <q>Tu potes vnanimes armare in praelia fratres, <note place="margin">Virgil Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid. lib. 7</note> atque odiis verſare domos.</q>
                  <p>thou it is who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtarme moſt louing bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one againſt the other, <hi>&amp;</hi> ouerthrow
<pb facs="tcp:10356:63"/> whole houſes and families with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious diſcorde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</head>
                  <p>Secondly it prouoketh to offer all <note place="margin">2. It pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh men to offer iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> indignities and wrongs to a mans neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as alſo to reuenge the ſmalleſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries without all proportion. For men incenſed with anger will wittingly and willingly reuenge thoſe iniuries, which haue vnwittingly and vnwillingly bene offered; for angry wordes they will giue blowes, for blowes vvounds, and for vvounds death. And therefore the vviſeman ſayth; <hi>That anger is cruell, and wrath is raging. Pro.</hi> 27. 4. Yea it prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro.</hi> 27. 4</note> men not onely to reuenge ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, but alſo no iniuries; for anger ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth euen againſt the innocents, &amp; that oftentimes becauſe they are innocent, and but too vertuous, as the furious man imagineth. And this is euident in the example of <hi>Cains</hi> anger agaynſt <hi>Abell, Saules</hi> agaynſt <hi>Ionathan</hi> and <hi>Dauid; Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezers</hi> agaynſt the three children, <hi>Herods</hi> againſt the innocents, the Scribes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10356:63"/> and Phariſeis agaynſt Chriſt as before I proued.</p>
                  <p>But as anger cauſeth men to be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to all others, ſo eſpecially to thoſe <note place="margin">Anger moſt hurt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</note> vvhom they ſhould moſt loue, cheriſh, and defend, that is, they who are of a mans owne familie. Who becauſe they are neceſſarily conuerſant with them, are continually ſubiect and euen expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to their fury and outrage: the wife to their bitter ſpeaches (if they do not worſe, that is, like madde men beate their owne fleſh) the children to furious and vnreaſonable correction, the ſeruants not onely to reuiling ſpeaches, but alſo to cruell ſtripes and blowes: ſo that (as one ſayth vvell) we may know an angry <note place="margin">Plutarch decohib. irac.</note> man if we but looke in the faces of his ſeruantes, namely by their ſcarres and bruiſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 11.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the priuate euils which <note place="margin">The euils which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to common wealther.</note> accompanie vniuſt anger; now we are to ſpeake of the publick. Vniuſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger is the cauſe of all tum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s and vproares, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions and conſpiracies, maſſakers and
<pb facs="tcp:10356:64"/> bloudy warres, yea the ouerthrow and confuſion of all cities and common wealthes. It is the cauſe which inciteth the magiſtrate agaynſt the ſubiect, and the ſubiect agaynſt the magiſtrate, the prince againſt the people, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt the prince, kingdome againſt kingdome, and nation agaynſt nation: and that not onely vppon waightie cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but alſo vppon trifling occaſions. For as to make a farious and vnquenchable flame, it is not materiall how ſmall the fire is that kindleth it, ſo the matter be apt to receaue it wherein it is kindled, for one coale is mough to burne a whole city, if it fall among flax, &amp; one ſparke if it light in tinder or gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>powder: ſo it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth not how ſmall the cauſe is which inflameth anger, for if the minde which receaueth it be ſubiect to be inflamed, it is ſufficient to ſet on fire and conſume vvhole kingdomes <hi>&amp;</hi> common wealths; eſpecially if power be correſpondent to the violence of the affection.</p>
                  <p>Infinite examples might be brought <note place="margin">Examples.</note> to make this manifeſt: as of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leuie,</hi> vvho in their anger put a vvhole <note place="margin">Gen. 34.</note> city to the ſword, though their quarell
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10356:64"/> were but to one man. Of <hi>Abimilech,</hi> who <note place="margin">Iudg. 9.</note> in his fury deſtroyed all the city of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem,</hi> of <hi>Saul</hi> deſtroying <hi>Nob,</hi> of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Heſt. 3</note> vvho being incenſed onely agaynſt <hi>Mordecay,</hi> layd a plot for the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole nation of the Iewes. But I ſhall not neede to ſtand vppon it, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not onely the booke of God, but alſo auncient hiſtories yea euen our owne cronicles and dayly experience do make this but too euident.</p>
                  <p>You ſee then the manifold euils which waite vppon this raging diſeaſe of the minde vniuſt anger, for it is not onely a deadly impoſtume breaking out in our ſelues, but alſo an infectious <hi>&amp;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious plague which deſtroieth whole peoples and commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>wealthes. with how greate care therefore ſhould we vſe all good meanes and wholeſome remedies, to preuent or cure ſuch a daungerous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The remedies of vniuſt anger. Cap.</hi> 7.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>The remedies againſt Anger are of two ſorts: firſt thoſe which cure anger in our
<pb facs="tcp:10356:65"/> ſelues, ſecondly thoſe which cure it in others; and they both are of two kindes: firſt ſuch as preuent anger and preſerue vs from falling into it, ſecondly ſuch as free vs from it after it hath taken place. For anger is a diſeaſe of the minde: as therefore vviſe Phyſitions thinke it the <note place="margin">We muſt firſt ſeeke to preuent anger.</note> better &amp; ſaufer courſe to preſerue health and preuent ſickneſſe, then to remoue the diſeaſe after it hath taken poſſeſſion of the body; ſo the beſt courſe in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſpirituall Phyſick is to preſerue the ſoule from vice, rather then to purge it away after it hath infected it; for <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia facilius repelluntur quam expelluntur,</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">Sen. epiſt 119.</note> are more eaſily kept from entrance then thruſt out after they are entred: for as the common prouerbe is; there are but twelue points in the lawe, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion is as good as eleauen of them. If therefore anger haue gotten poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, vve ſhall hardlye diſpoſſeſſe it: It is our ſoules mortall enemie; as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vve firſt ſeeke to keepe the enemie from entring the frontires of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, but if he be entred, as ſoone as we can to expell him, ſo wee muſt firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to repell anger by ſtopping the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10356:65"/> paſſages of our harts, that it may haue no entrance, but if it haue taken place, quickly to expell and remooue it. For if we ſuffer it to fortifie it ſelfe, it will growe ſo ſtrong and violent, that wee ſhall be vnable to diſlodge it. And as in a ſiedge of a City the Citizens prouide all things neceſſary for their defence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the aſſault, that the enemie when hee approacheth the walles, may not take them vnprouided; ſo if we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell anger when it commeth, we are to fortifie and arme our ſelues againſt it before it comes: for if it take vs vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, it will eaſely make entrance, and more eaſely ouercome vs.</p>
                  <p>Let vs therefore firſt of allendeauour to vſe all good meanes by which we may preuent anger: for if it haue once got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hould of vs, it will eaſelie plunge vs headlong into vyolence and furie, whereas wee may with greater facillity preuent the daunger before we fall into it. For as experience teacheth vs, a man may eaſelye contayne himſelfe from running downe the hill, while hee is on the toppe, but after he is entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a full race, hee cannot ſtave himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:10356:66"/> before he commeth to the bottome: ſo it is more eaſie for any to abſtaine from running into anger, then to containe vvhen he is in the race, from falling into the bottome of furie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>Let vs then ſee the meanes how to <note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes therof are to be remoued.</note> preuent anger: the firſt remedy is by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the cauſes thereof for: <hi>ſublat â cauſ â tollitur effectum.</hi> The cauſe being taken away the effect ceaſeth.</p>
                  <p>The firſt cauſe of anger is ſelfe loue. If therefore we would not fall into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <note place="margin">1. Selfe-loue.</note> we muſt labour to baniſh ſelfe loue, and to follow the rule of charitie; <hi>Loue our neighbours as our ſelues, and do nothing vnto them which we would not haue them do vnto vs.</hi> Before therefore wee let the raines looſe vnto our anger, let vs ſet our ſelues in the place of him with whome we are angrie, and conſider how we would deſire to be vſed if we had ſo offended, and in like manner are we to behaue our ſelues towards him. So ſhall we not aggrauate thoſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iuries vvhich are offered vs, &amp; extenuate thoſe which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10356:66"/> we offer others, ſo ſhall we not haue our iudgement ouer ballanced with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall affection, ſo ſhall we not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed for ſuffring that, which we haue often offred.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3</head>
                  <p>The ſecond cauſe of anger is pride and <note place="margin">2. Pride.</note> haughtineſſe of ſpirit: if therefore we would not fall into anger, we are to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due pride, and labour for the contrarie grace of humilitie. For they who would be meeke with our Sauiour Chriſt, muſt alſo learne of him the leſſon of true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 29. <hi>Learne of me, for I</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 11. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>am meeke and lowlie of hart.</hi> If we would lay aſide that arrogant conceipt vvhich we haue of our ſelues, and the ouerwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning opinion of our owne excellencies, if we would conſider with <hi>Abraham</hi> that <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 27. Pſa. 22. 6.</note> vve are but <hi>duſt and aſhes,</hi> and with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> that vve <hi>are wormes and no men;</hi> or if we vvould in ſincerity of hart ſay with <hi>Iob, Vnto corruption thou art my father, and vnto the worme, thou art my mother and my</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 17. 14</note> 
                     <hi>ſiſter;</hi> If vve would but remember that by our ſinnes committed againſt God &amp; our neighbour, we haue deſerued not
<pb facs="tcp:10356:67"/> onely contumelies and wrongs, but alſo eternall death of body and ſoule; wee would not ſo eaſely be prouoked to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vppon euery trifling occaſion, nor thinke it any great diſparagement to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure leſſer iniuries, ſeeing we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued farre greater.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>The third cauſe is couetouſneſſe, which uice we muſt baniſh out of our harts, if <note place="margin">3. Couetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</note> we would not be ouercome with vniuſt anger: ſo ſhall wee not gape after great preferments, nor expect much; and conſequentlie wee ſhall not be diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with vnquietneſſe, nor incenſed with anger, vvhen vve come not ſhorte of our hopes. So ſhall wee not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with euery domeſticall trifle, but commit ſome thing to the care of ſeruants, ſome thing to children, and moſt of all to the wyfe, who is a ioynte gouernour in thy little common wealth. And if any thing miſcarry vnder any of theyr handes, wee will not ſo much looke to the meanes, as to the ſupreame cauſe, the prouidence of God, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:10356:67"/> that if he builde not the houſe, they labour in vaine that builde it, if he bleſſe <note place="margin">Pſa. 127. 1</note> not their labours they cannot proſper.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p>The fourth cauſe is luxuriouſneſſe and curious niceneſſe; if therefore we <note place="margin">Luxurious niceneſſe.</note> would ſubdue anger, we muſt ſubdue this vice alſo, and labour to attaine vnto decent homelineſſe, the Nurſe of good hoſpitallity, and the preſeruer of peace and quietneſſe: for if with our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> wee were clothed vvith skinnes, that is with meane attyre, we would not be ſo eaſilye prouoked to anger if a ſpotte or wrinckle bee found vppon our garments; if with them we did feede vppon rootes and hearbes, vve vvould not eate with ſurfeyted and cloyed appetites, and conſequently (our meates being ſauced with hunger) our taſtes would not be ſo wantonly curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that no ordinary cookery can pleaſe them. If with <hi>Abraham</hi> we dwelled in tents like Pilgrimes, we vvould not be ſo nice in decking our houſes, nor ſo angry
<pb facs="tcp:10356:68"/> for a Copweb; If vvith <hi>Iacob</hi> vve had the earth for our bed, a ſtone for our pillo we, and the skye for our Canopie, vve vvould not be ſo much diſpleaſed for the hardneſſe of a featherbed, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſineſſe of a doune lodging: take away therefore luxurious niceneſſe, and you ſhall take away alſo the moſt common cauſe of vniuſt anger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>The fift cauſe of vniuſt anger, is vaine curioſitie, in deſiring to heare and ſee all <note place="margin">5 Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie.</note> things. If therefore we vvould auoyde anger, vve are to abandon this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome companion, needleſſe curioſitie. For many things will neither grieue nor hurte vs, if we neuer ſee nor heare them. Whereas hee that buſilye enquireth vvhat is ſaid againſt him in euery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, hee that liſteneth at euery doore, and vnder euery vvall, he that rippeth vp ill words ſpoken againſt him in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, doth both diſquiet himſelfe vvith anger, and make his owne faultes more publicke. <hi>Antigonus</hi> vvhen he heard
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10356:68"/> two of his ſubiects ſpeaking euill of him in the night neare his Tent, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto them, vvilling them to goe further off leaſt the King ſhould heare them. Whoſe example if vve vvould follow, our anger vvould not ſo much vexe our ſelues, nor trouble others.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
                  <p>The ſixt cauſe is, to haue open cares to euery tale-bearer, and credulous harts <note place="margin">6 Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> to belieue them. For it is the nature of men, to be moſt deſirous of hearing that vvhich moſt diſpleaſeth them, <hi>Et liben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter credere quae inuitè audiunt,</hi> vvillinglye <note place="margin">Senec. de ira lib. 2. cap. 22.</note> to beleeue thoſe things vvhich they are moſt ſorie to heare. But if vvee vvould auoide vniuſt anger, vve muſt auoide this vice alſo: <hi>Multos abſoluemus</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Senec de ira. lib. 3 cap. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>ſi caeperimus ante iudicare quam iraſci,</hi> wee ſhall acquit many, if vve vvill not bee angrye before vve iudge. Let vs not therefore ſuffer execution to goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore iudgement, but rather deferre our more ſeuere cenſure, till time haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed the truth, conſidering that
<pb facs="tcp:10356:69"/> it is moſt vſuall with men to reporte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes, ſome that they may deceiue thee, ſome becauſe they are deceiued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeues, ſome becauſe they would ſet friends at variance, ſome in their accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation will faine an iniurye offered vs, that they may take occaſion to ſhewe their ſorrow, becauſe it was offred; but ſcarce any of them will ſtand to that vvhich they haue ſpoken. And therefore let vs not be angry before wee iudge, nor iudge before vve heare both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: For vvhat iniuſtice is it to haue both eares open to an accuſation, and both ſhut to an excuſe? to proceede to ſentence of condemnation, before vve aske the party accuſed vvhat he can ſay for himſelfe? vvhat greater vvronge then to beleeue in ſecret, and to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry openly?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
                  <p>The laſt cauſe of vniuſt anger, is want <note place="margin">7. Want of medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities.</note> of meditation, concerning humaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, eyther thoſe which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all mankinde, or thoſe which are more proper and peculiar to our ſelues.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:10356:69"/> if therefore we would be reſtravned from anger, we muſt often thinke of this contagious leproſie of originall ſin, which hath ſo generally infected al the the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> that their remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing in vs but pollution and filthineſſe. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as one infected with the plague, is not offended with him that is ſubiect to the ſame infection; As the Lazar doth neyther with ſcorne nor choller, but rather with pitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion behould the ſores of his fellowe: ſo the plague and ſore of ſinne which we ſee in another, wil not make vs angry with the partie which is affected and viſited, but rather in commiſeration and pity to vſe all good meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may be cured, if we conſider that this plague and ſore of ſinne is ſo vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall that it hath infected all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</p>
                  <p>When worde was brought to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxagoras</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Plutarch, de cohib, irac.</note> that is ſonne was dead, he was not much moued with the newes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as he ſaid) he knew and had conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered long before that his ſonne was mortall: ſo if we would conſider and meditate on humane frayltie and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<pb facs="tcp:10356:70"/> we ſhould not be ſo much vexed when they did ſhewe themſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not happen beyond our expectation. If he that hireth a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant would thinke with himſelfe, that he hireth one who is not free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faults, if hee that choſeth a friend would then conſider that he hath his wants and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections: If he that maryeth a wife would remember that hee maryeth a woman, and therefore one ſubiect to infirmities: neyther the ſmall faultes of his ſeruants, nor imperfections of his friendes, nor infirmities of his wife, would eaſily prouoke him to choller &amp; fury, ſeeing he did not come ſhort of his reckoning.</p>
                  <p>More ouer we are to meditate vppon our owne peculiar infirmities and wants, and before we are angry with another to enter into our ſelues, and to ſay with <note place="margin">Plutarch. de cohib. irac.</note> 
                     <hi>Plato: Nuncubi et ego talis?</hi> haue not I alſo offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in this, or in that which is worſe? am I cleare from offering the like iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or greater to my bretheren? Alas no, but though I were, yet how often haue I prouoked God to anger by my ſinnes? for which great debt how can I craue
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10356:70"/> pardon, if I cruelly exact euery trifle of of my fellow ſeruant? Thus if we would ſpeake vnto our owne conſciences in the preſence of God, we would not ſo eaſily be incited to anger and reuenge, ſeeing we our ſelues doe many things which neede pardon; and our greater faultes might ſerue to excuſe thoſe which are leſſe in others, if we would but looke vppon them: for no man without bluſhing could extreamely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thoſe faultes in his neighbour, for vvhich he ſhall neede to craue pardon himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>And ſo much concerning the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie of anger which is by remouing the cauſes thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſecond meanes to ſubdue anger is</hi> to labour for patience. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond meanes to ſubdue anger is to labour for the contrarie vertue of patience and long ſuffering. And to <note place="margin">All things happen by Gods owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence. Rom 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> this end we are firſt to conſider that nothing happeneth vnto vs without Gods al ſeeing prouidence, who if we be his children will diſpoſe of euery thing
<pb facs="tcp:10356:71"/> for our good. Why therefore ſhould we vex our ſelues with anger, ſeeing God will turne the iniuries of men into bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings? let vs rather when any wrong is offered vs, which we cannot by iuſt and lawfull meanes auoyd, ſay with our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18. 11. ſhould not I drinke of the cup which my father hath <note place="margin">Ioh. 18. 11</note> prouided for me? ſhould I be angry with the cup becauſe the phyſicke is bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? or with the hand whereby it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayghed vnto me? My heauenly father correcteth me for my good and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I will not therefore be angry with the rod wherwith I am beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather looke to the hand vvhich inflicteth the chaſtiſment, and I vvill ſay vvith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. Pſal.</hi> 139. 10. <hi>I am dumbe and do not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſa: 139. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>open my mouth becauſe thou doeſt it.</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I ſhould commit as great folly as he, who is angry vvith the ſtaffe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is beaten, and neuer regardeth the ſmiter, and ſhewe my ſelfe as madde as the dogge, vvho looketh not to the caſter, but vvreaketh his anger by biting <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> the ſtone.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:10356:71"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>Secondly we are to conſider that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries which we haue receiued are much <note place="margin">Our iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued leſſe then our ſinnes haue deſerued.</note> leſſe then by our ſinnes vve haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued; for they are but light, or if not light yet momentary, but our ſinnes haue deſerued infinite and eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments. If therefore the Lord vſe theſe earthly rods to correct our ſinnes; vve are rather to admire his mercie then to be angry at ſo gentle chaſtizemenr. let vs therfore looke vppon our ſinnes and not vppon our puniſhment, and ſo ſhall vve patiently beare the iniury of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered as ſent from God, becauſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of him it is no iniury, and not as it is inflicted by man, and be readie to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> vvho vvhen he vvas iniuriouſly abuſed by <hi>Shemei,</hi> vvas not prouoked by anger to take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, becauſe he looked not vppon <hi>Shemei,</hi> as being but<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the inſtrument, but vppon God vvho vvas the author. <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 10. 11.</note> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 10. 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10356:72"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>The third meanes to ſubdue anger <note place="margin">3. Meanes to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on Chriſts Paſsion.</note> by arming vs with patience, is to call continually to rememberance the bitter paſſion and ſufferings of Chriſt for our ſinnes. For if we conſider how patiently he indured ſcoffes and reproches, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and reuiling, buffeting and ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, yea death it ſelfe, and the anger of God more grieuous then death, not for any demerit of his, but for our ſakes, we may eaſily ſuffer ſuch ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries as are offered vnto vs by men, at our ſauiour Chriſtes requeſt, ſeeing we <note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9. Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 21. 6</note> haue deſerued farre greater. As therefore thoſe which were ſtong with the fiery ſerpentes, were healed if they did looke vp to the braſen ſerpent which was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected for this end: ſo if this fiery ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of vniuſt anger haue ſtong vs, and the burning poyſon thereof hath infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs, let vs caſt the eyes of our ſoules vppon the true braſen ſerpent, our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt hanging vppon the croſſe, and ſuffering the wrath of God due to our ſinnes, and ſo the heate of our wrath
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:10356:72"/> and anger vvill ſoone be cured and cooled.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>The fourth meanes to worke pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <note place="margin">4. The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this dutie.</note> and repell anger is to conſider the neceſſitie hereof, for if the loue of our bretheren be not of more force to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuenge, then anger to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vs thereunto, we can haue no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that we are the children of God. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 10. <hi>In this are the children of God</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3. 10. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>knowne and the children of the deuill, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer doth not righteouſneſſe, is not of God nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be that loueth not his brother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo verſe</hi> 15. <hi>Whoſoeuer hateth his brother is a man ſlayer, and no manſlayer hath eternall life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſome wil ſay, though I am raſhly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, yet may I loue my brother. I anſwer with the Apoſtle 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 4. 7. that loue <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13 4. 7.</note> both ſuffereth long &amp; ſuffreth al things: and therefore they want this loue who will ſuffer nothing, and be prouoked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery minute, nay he ſayth expreſly in the fift verſe, <hi>that loue is not prouoked to Anger.</hi> that is, to raſh and vniuſt anger; and therefore they are deſtitute
<pb facs="tcp:10356:73"/> of loue vvho are ſo eaſily prouoked.</p>
                  <p>Secondly it is moſt neceſſarie to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due anger, becauſe while we remayne therein vve can haue no aſſurance that our praiers are acceptably hard of God; not onely becauſe we pray ſo to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen as vve forgiue, and therefore if vve retayne our anger towards our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, vve pray that God vvill retayne his towardes vs; but alſo becauſe our ſauiour expreſly telleth vs, <hi>That if we do not remit men their treſpaſſes our heauenly father will not forgiue vs our ſinnes. Ma.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 6. 15.</note> 6. 15. And that <hi>with what meaſure we mete vnto others it ſhalbe meaſured vnto vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. Math.</hi> 7. 2. Let vs remember the <note place="margin">Math. 7. 2</note> parable of the ſeruant vvho beeing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen ten thouſand talents, and after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting vvith all crueltie of his fellow ſeruant an hundreth pence, vvas caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the priſon of vtter darkeneſſe. <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 23. Whereby thus much is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <note place="margin">Mat, 11. 23</note> that if vve vvill not fogiue ſmall iniuries to our bretheren, ſeeing the Lord hath forgiuen our infinite hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſinnes, vve ſhall be vſed like that mercileſſe and cruell ſeruant. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs follow the counſell of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:10356:73"/> Apoſtle. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 32. <hi>Be courtcous one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother and tender harted, freely forgiuing one</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 32</note> 
                     <hi>another, euen as God for Chriſts ſake freelye forgaue you.</hi> And ſo much for the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this dutie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p>The fift meanes to arme vs with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience againſt the aſſaults of anger, is <note place="margin">5. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of patience in others.</note> that we propound vnto our ſelues the examples of others: for the looking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon greene collour is not more ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, for thoſe who are troubled with inflamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the eyes, then the behould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the clemencie and patience of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is for thoſe whoſe harts are infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with anger. Firſt therefore let vs ſet before vs the example of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who is <hi>mercifull, gratious, and ſlowe to anger,</hi> as himſelfe deſcribeth himſelfe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6. And hereof the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <note place="margin">Exo. 34. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> taſted by often experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and therefore hee ſaith likewiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 8. <hi>The Lorde is full of compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſa: 163. 8 9</note> 
                     <hi>and mercie, ſlowe to anger and of great kindneſſe.</hi> And as hee is not eaſely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to anger, ſo beeing prouoked
<pb facs="tcp:10356:74"/> his anger laſteth not long; for <hi>Hee will not alway chide, nor keepe his anger for euer,</hi> as it is verſe 9. Nay no ſooner can we knock at the gate of his mercy, but he is ready to open, as he hath promiſed, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 7. If therefore wee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble our heauenly Father, and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue <note place="margin">Math. 7. 7</note> our ſelues to be his children, we muſt learne to imitate his patience and long ſuffering.</p>
                  <p>Secondly wee are to propound vnto vs the example of our Sauiour Chriſt, the liuelie character &amp; expreſſe Image of his father, as he exhorteth vs. <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 29. <note place="margin">Math. 11. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>Learne of me for I am meeke and lowlie of hart, and you ſhall finde reſt to your ſoules.</hi> What this meekeneſſe was, <hi>Peter</hi> telleth vs. 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 2. 22. <hi>Though he were free from ſinne, and had no guile found in his mouthe,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 22</note> 
                     <hi>yet when hee was reuiled, he reuiled not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and when hee ſuffered hee threatned not.</hi> Though in reſpect of his infinite power, he vvas able not onely to haue threatned, but alſo to haue vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed his enemies. If therefore Chriſt was ſo milde and patient, vvho vvas free from ſinne, ſurely much more
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:10356:74"/> ſhould wee be (if it vvere poſſible) who by our ſinnes haue deſerued the greateſt iniuries, yea eternall death.</p>
                  <p>But if theſe examples be too high for our imitation, let vs caſt the eyes of our mindes vppon the patience and long ſuffering of our fellow bretheren. As of <hi>Abraham,</hi> vvho vvhen iuſt cauſe of offence was offered by <hi>Lot</hi> and his Shepheards, vvas rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to part from his right, then hee would haue any diſcorde and diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. 8. Of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> who then <note place="margin">Gen. 13. 8</note> was ready to pray for the people, vvhen they were ready to ſtone him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17. <note place="margin">Exo. 17. 4 11.</note> 4. 11. Of <hi>Dauid</hi> who hauing reuendge in his owne hand, vvhen hee vvas prouoked by the out-ragious iniuries of <hi>Shemei,</hi> did notwithſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine himſelfe, 2. <hi>Samu.</hi> 16. 10. and of <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Steuen,</hi> vvho vvhen the ſtones ſlewe about his eares, prayed for his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that threw them at him, <hi>Acts</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Act. 7. 60 The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 7. 60.</p>
                  <p>Or if theſe examples will not moue vs to the loue of myldeneſſe and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, let vs ſet before our eyes thoſe men
<pb facs="tcp:10356:75"/> which are ſubiect to the furie of anger, and ſo ſhall we eaſely diſcerne in others what an vglie and brutiſh vice it is in our ſelues. One ſaith, that if an angrye man would looke himſelfe in a Glaſſe <note place="margin">Senec. lib. 2. de ira cap. 36.</note> in the middeſt of his furie, he would appeare ſo horrible in his own ſight, that it would be a notable meanes to worke an hatred in his hart, of ſo deformed a vice; but for as much as angry men will hardly be brought to this while they continue in their rage, or if they could, they haue ſomewhat relented already, and ſo the coppy of their countenance is chaunged; or though it were not, the furie of their affection ſo cloudeth the iudgement of reaſon, that they thinke all things become them vvhich they do in theyr paſſion: Let vs therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the example of the <hi>Spartanes,</hi> vvho vvould cauſe their children to looke vppon their <hi>Hellottes</hi> and ſlaues vvhen they were drunken, that they might be brought into deteſtation of ſo vglie a vice, vvhen they beheld the beaſtlineſſe thereof in others: So let vs ſet before our eyes other men,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10356:75"/> while they be in their furie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how it deformeth the body, and diſableth the minde, the lamentable tragedies which it acteth, and follies vvhich it committeth; and the vglie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie, ioyned with brutiſh follye, muſt needes mooue vs to hate ſo foule a vice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>The ſixt meanes is to abſtayne from multitude of buſineſſe, becauſe not <note place="margin">6. To ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multitude of buſines.</note> onelie the minde is diſtracted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed therewith, and ſo made a fitte Inne for anger to lodge in, but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in ſuch aboundance of buſineſſe, ſome things of neceſſitye will miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and among ſuch a multitude of Irons, ſome will burne, and ſo inflame the minde to anger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10356:76"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
                  <p>The ſeauenth meanes, is to auoide <note place="margin">7. To ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentious contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies. Senec. lib. 3. de ira Cap. 8.</note> contentious controuerſies; for <hi>facilius eſt a certamine abstinere quam abducere,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be very eaſie to abſtaine from them before they are begunne, yet after a man is entred into them, he cannot ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie giue them ouer. Becauſe he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that it will derogate from his witte and iudgement, if he be forced to yeelde though it be to a truth: and beſides men naturally deſire to bring others to be of their opinion, and therefore they will vſe great earneſtneſſe to perſwade, and often times burſt out into anger and furie, if they cannot obtayne their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
                  <p>The eyght meanes to preuent anger, <note place="margin">8. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the companie of colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick men. Pro. 22. 24</note> is to auoyde the company of thoſe who are angrie and chollerick: becauſe men will eaſilie bee infected with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion. And this <hi>Salomon</hi> teacheth vs. <hi>Pro.</hi> 22. 24. <hi>Make no friendſhip with an</hi>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:10356:76"/> 
                     <hi>angrie man, neither go with the furious man, least thou learne his wayes and receaue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to thy ſoule.</hi> And alſo becauſe they are likely to be prouoked by them, and to receaue the heate of their flame. For as one ſticke of wood beeing ſet on fire, doth kindle that alſo which is next vnto it: So one man beeing inflamed with anger, inflameth them alſo who are neere about him with his prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
                  <p>Laſtly, thoſe who finde themſelues <note place="margin">9. To bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle anger for a day.</note> by nature prone to anger, are to labour, and as it were to vow with themſelues, that they will containe their furie for one day, whatſoeuer occaſion ſhall bee offered, and after that another, and a third, and ſo by little and little they ſhall attaine vnto an habit of patience, and cuſtome will alter nature.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:10356:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The remedies to expell or</hi> bridle Anger. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.</head>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>ANd ſo much for thoſe meanes and remedies, whereby we may preuent and repell anger before wee fall into it. Now in the next place I will ſet downe, how we are to behaue our ſelues after that anger hath made an entrance, and taken place in vs. And this the Apoſtle teacheth vs in the reſtraint: <hi>Let not the Sunne goe downe on your wrathe.</hi> That is, if thorough infirmitie yee fall into vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt anger, yet continue not in it, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abandon this corrupt affection with all poſſible ſpeede. So that our anger muſt not ſleepe with vs, and after wee awake, awake alſo; we muſt not vſe it like our garments, laye it aſide ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, with a purpoſe to take it againe the next daye: but rather vvee are to put it off lyke the olde man, with full reſolution neuer agayne to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne or aſſume it, or like ſome pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ragges vvhich are not vvorthe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:10356:77" rendition="simple:additions"/> the wearing. And this muſt wee doe not once or twiſe, but if euery day with the ſunne anger ariſe in our harts, we are euery day to diſlodge and expell it, before the ſunne going downe. And as the night doth coole the heate which in the day time the ſunne hath made; ſo muſt it alſo quench the flames of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger kindled in our harts. And not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">The daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> great reaſon he requireth that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore night commeth, we abandon anger, for otherwiſe we ſhall giue place to the diuells tentations, as he intimateth in the wordes following: for hauing exhorted, vs not to let the ſunne goe down on our wrath he preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly addeth: <hi>Neyther giue place to the diuell.</hi> Noting thereby that they who do not onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine anger in the day, but alſo lodge it in the night, do thereby lay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues open to the fiery darts of Sathan. <hi>For he continually goeth about like a roaring ſeeking</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 8,</note> 
                     <hi>whom he may deuoure.</hi> And when he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſuch as haue retayned anger euen in their beds, thinking them a fit pray, he approcheth &amp; with his bellowes of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he more inflameth the fire of anger, till it flameth out into furious reuenge.
<pb facs="tcp:10356:78"/> he aggrauateth the iniury receiued, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that if they put vp ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity, they wil expoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the like, or for ſuffering this looſe all their credit and reputation, by incurring the note of cowardize. And ſo hauing wrought in their harts a full reſolution to take reuenge, in the next place he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth into their heades the moſt fitte meanes and oportunitie of performing it with all rage and cruelty. And ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times it commeth to paſſe that when they ariſe, they put that in practiſe which they haue deuiſed lying vppon their pillow.</p>
                  <p>To preuent therefore ſo great an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil; if we cannot altogeather repel anger, yet let vs ſoone expell it. For though at the firſt it be but a ſmall ſparke, yet if it bee nouriſhed it will quicklye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to a furious flame. As therefore when a houſe is newly ſet on fire, men labour earneſtly, and with all ſpeede to to quench it, before it haue taken hould of the mayne poaſtes and great beames; otherwiſe it will be too late afterward, when it is increaſed to his full ſtrength:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:10356:78"/> ſo when our heartes are firſt ſet on fire with anger, we are preſently to quench it, with the water of the ſpirit, for after we are throughly enflamed, it wilbe too late to apply any remedie till the flame hauc ſpent it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But ſome will ſay, I fall into anger ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times when I neuer meane it, and it <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection </seg>
                     </label> hath ouercome me before I am aware; how therefore ſhould I preuent that which I do not foreſee, or free my ſelfe from it, ſeeing it violently ouerruleth me? <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the firſt I anſwere; that if we care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully watch ouer our ſelues wee ſhall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceaue when we are inclining to anger: for as there are many ſignes vvhich goe before a ſtorme, and many ſymptomes vvhich diſcouer diſeaſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we fall into them: So we may eaſily diſcerne in our ſelues many notes and ſignes, of this tempeſtuous ſtorme and raging feuer of the minde, vniuſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
                  <p>To the other I anſwere; that anger doth not preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly as ſoone as it is entred into the hart ouerrule vs, before it be growne
<pb facs="tcp:10356:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> to greater ſtrength then it hath at the firſt, for as the greateſt fire hath but a ſmall beginning, and when it hath but begun, is eaſily que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched: ſo the moſt fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious anger attayneth not to his full ſtrength at the firſt entrance; but by little and little increaſeth like a flame, by taking hould of new matter. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore howſoeuer after it hath wholy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed a man, it is moſt hardly quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, yet in the beginning thereof, it is eaſily ſuppreſſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>But let vs ſee the meanes how <note place="margin">The firſt meanes to withdraw the foode thereof.</note> we may ſubdue anger after it hath giuen the aſſault. The meanes is by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing the foode from it, wherwith it is nouriſhed. For as the greateſt fire if new matter be not ſupplied will of it ſelfe go out: ſo the moſt furious anger will ſoone be mitigated, if it be not continually nouriſhed with a new ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of matter. <note place="margin">Multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of words the chiefe foode of anger.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The cheife nouriſhment vvhereby anger is nouriſhed and increaſed, is mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying of vvords, for though the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:10356:79"/> at the firſt be ſmall, yet if eyther it be aggrauated by him that ſuffereth it, or defended by him that offereth it, it incenſeth men to great anger. Well therefore in this reſpect may wordes be ſayd to be but vvinde; for as nothing ſooner then vvinde cauſeth a ſmall ſparke to burſt out into a furious flame: ſo nothing ſooner doth cauſe a ſmall ſpark of anger increaſe to a raging flame of reuenge, then the vvinde of vvordes. We are not therefore to imagine vvith ſome, that wee can diſgorge our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks of anger by vomitting our ſpleane in bitter vvordes; for they do not onely in their owne nature whet and ſharpen our owne affections, but alſo prouoke the other with vvhom vve are offended to requite vs vvith the like, and ſo to adde new matter to the old flame. As vvell therefore may we think to quench the fire vvith vvood, as anger with vvordes, for as vvood is the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the fire, ſo vvordes are then ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of anger. Let vs rather in our anger imitate the vviſe <hi>Socrates,</hi> vvho vvhen hee vvas moſt angrye vſed moſt <note place="margin">Plutarch. decohib. irac.</note> modeſty mildeneſſe of ſpeach &amp; lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:10356:80"/> of voice, and ſo vvithdrawing the nouriſhment from the fire of anger, it will ſoone of it ſelfe be extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond meanes to ſubdue anger, <note place="margin">The 2. meanes to withdraw a mans ſelfe out of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. 1. Sam. 20 34.</note> is to get out of the companie of others, eſpecially of them vvho haue offended vs, according to the example of <hi>Ionathan</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 34. vvho beeing iuſtly prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by his vniuſt and cruell father, roſe from the table and departed, leaſt by his fathers prouocations, hee might haue done or ſayd that vvhich did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme him. vvhoſe practiſe if we would imitate, we ſhal not only appeaſe our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by remouing out of our ſight the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect &amp; cauſe therof; and preuent further occaſions of increaſing it, but alſo couer our infirmities, vvhich otherwiſe vvee ſhould diſcouer by the violence of the paſſion.</p>
                  <p>As therefore they who are vexed with the falling ſickneſſe (if they cannot by their ordinarie remedies preuent their
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:10356:80"/> fit) wil go out of the company of others, that falling ſecretly, they may haue noe witneſſe of their deformity; ſo they who are not able to curbe in their anger with the rayne of reaſon, were beſt to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe themſelues and to keepe priuate, vvhile their fit laſteth; that ſo they may hide the vgglineſſe of their vice, which being ſeene doth often moue their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries to ſcorne and laughter, and their friendes to ſorrow and pity. And this is made a note of a vviſe man by the vviſeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 12. 16. <hi>A foole in a day ſhalbe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 16</note> 
                     <hi>knowne by his anger, but he that couereth his ſhame is wiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>The third meanes to vanquiſh anger, <note place="margin">The 3. meanes to reſtrain it for a while fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burſting out into fury.</note> is for a vvhile to bridle and reſtrayne it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burſting out into preſent reuenge. For if we reſiſt it in the firſt encounter, we ſhall finde the ſtrength thereof much vveakened. <hi>&amp;</hi> this the wiſe <hi>Athenodorus</hi> knew wel; who being to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus,</hi> was requeſted by him that he would <note place="margin">Plutarch. in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10356:81"/> leaue behinde him ſome good inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the vvell gouerning of his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, to whom he gaue this counſayle, that he ſhould do nothing in his anger, before he had numbred on his fingers the letters of the Greeke <hi>Alphabet.</hi> An example hereof vve haue in <hi>Socrates,</hi> vvho finding his anger incenſed againſt his ſeruant, deferred to take correction, ſaying: <hi>I would beate thee if I were not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Senec de ira li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cap. 15</note> And alſo in <hi>Plato,</hi> vvho being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to anger by ſome notable fault committed by his ſeruant, tooke a cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell into his hands, and held it ouer him a good ſpace, as if he would haue ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; And being aſked of his friend <hi>Speu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſippus,</hi> vvhat he meant by ſuch kinde of act on. O (ſayd he) <hi>Exigo paenas ab homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne iracundo.</hi> I take puniſhment of one <note place="margin">Senec. de ira lib. 3. cap. 12.</note> vvho is angry; meaning of himſelfe, by bridling his affection. If then the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could thus deferre and curbe in their vnruly paſſions; vvho had onely the ſmall glimſe of natures light, and heathen Philoſophie to direct them; let vs be aſhamed to come behinde them, ſeeing vve haue not onely that, but alſo the bright ſunne ſhine of the vvorde of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:10356:81"/> God to guide vs.</p>
                  <p>And that wee may the rather be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to abſtaine from ſuddaine and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate reſolutions when our anger is prouoked, let vs conſider, that we are in great daunger to do thoſe things in a moment, which wee ſhall repent our whole life; for <hi>Ira breuis furor:</hi> Anger is a ſhort madneſſe. That in ſuch ſhortneſſe of time we cannot rightly examine the circumſtances of the matter, which in ſuch eaſes are moſt materiall, vvhereas <hi>veritatem dies aperiet.</hi> Truth is the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of time, and will bring all to light. <hi>Quicquid voles quale ſit ſcire tempori trade. Nihil diligenter in fluctu cernitur.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou wouldeſt be perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <note place="margin">Senec. de ira. lib. 3 cap. 12.</note> of, commit it to time, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is thoroughlie knowne on the ſuddaine. That it is a foule ſhame, firſt to be angrie, and then to iudge, firſt to take puniſhment, and then to examine the cauſe; that is to ſay, whether hath offended, he that taketh puniſhment, or he on whom it is inflicted: whereas in proceſſe of time the truth will appeare, whether reuenge may be more iuſtlie taken or omitted. And then if after due
<pb facs="tcp:10356:82"/> examination hee inflict deſerued pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, it will bee more effectuall for the reformation of the offendour, when he ſeeth that it doth rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from true iudgement, then from the ſpleene. As therefore <hi>Phocion</hi> ſayde to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> vvhen by hearing of <hi>Alexanders</hi> death, they were thereby moued to vſe more vnbrideled ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and inſolent practiſes. <hi>O yee</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians <hi>if</hi> Alexander <hi>be dead to day, hee will be dead to morrowe alſo;</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Plutarc. de cohib. ira.</note> you may well deferre theſe courſes, till yee be fully informed in the truth: ſo may I ſay to the angrie man: do not ſo haſtilie reuenge thy ſelfe on thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, for if it be a fault to day, it will be a fault to morrowe alſo: and as one <note place="margin">Senec. lib. 2. de ira ca. 23.</note> ſaith, <hi>Poteſt paena dilata exigi, non poteſt exacta reuocari;</hi> Puniſhment delayed may bee inflicted, but beeing inflicted it cannot be recalled. <hi>Non peribit pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas iſta ſi differetur. Sine id tempus veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at quo ipſi iubeamus.</hi> Thy power to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <note place="margin">Senec de ira. lib. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 32.</note> beeing deferred is not loſt: let it therefore ſo long bee delayed, till thy ſelfe may commaunde the puniſhment
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:10356:82"/> to be inflicted, and not thy paſſion of anger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p>The fourth meanes to ſubdue anger is this: Let the angrie man thinke with <note place="margin">The 4. meanes.</note> himſelfe whether he is purpoſed euer or neuer, to laye aſide his anger. If euer, how much better were it that he ſhould leaue his anger, then that it ſhould leaue him? that he ſhould vanquiſh it, then that it ſhould be ouer come of it ſelfe? that he ſhould quenche it with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſpirit, then that it ſhould laſt vntill it burne out? for not onely this but all other paſſions will in time tyre themſelues, and fall downe vvith their owne ruine. But if they purpoſe to liue in perpetuall enmity, let them conſider that they nouriſh in themſelues a Viper, vvhich vvill fret out their owne bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els. For vvho receiueth more vexation griefe and diſquietneſſe by anger then himſelfe, vvho is ſubiect to the
<pb facs="tcp:10356:83"/> paſſion? and what doth ſooner cut off the thred of life, then the ſharpneſſe of fretting griefe? Laſtlve, let him thinke with himſelfe what good time he ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in a badde matter, which being ſo ſhorte and precious, ſhould bee more eſteemed and better imployed; as in ſeeking to get friends, and not to looſe them being gotten by vniuſt anger, in pacifying and reconciling enemies, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then exaſperating them by offring new iniuries; in performing the workes of charity &amp; Chriſtianity: that ſo we may heare at the latter day that comfortable ſentence. <hi>Come yee bleſſed and inherite the kingdome prepared for you: For I was an</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 34</note> 
                     <hi>hungred and you gaue me meate, &amp;c.</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in acting the workes of the fleſh, among which anger is numbred, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 20. which who ſo commit ſhall <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 20.</note> not inherite the kingdome of God, but ſhall heare that fearefull ſentence, <hi>Goe yee curſed into euerlaſting fire, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the diuell and his angels.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 25. 41.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:10356:83"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>The laſt and chiefe meanes both to <note place="margin">The laſt meanes feruent prayer.</note> keepe vs from falling into anger, and to ſubdue it after it hath taken hould of vs, is earneſt and hartye prayer vnto God, that he would vouchſafe vs the gratious aſſiſtance of his holy ſpirite, vvhereby our affections may be ſo ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſanctified, that they being freed from naturall corruption, may be made fit and ſeruiceable for the ſetting forth of his glory, the good of our brethren, and the furthering of our owne ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For it is only the water of the ſpirit, and the ſhield of faith, which is able to quenche the furie of our paſſions; and prayer is a chiefe meanes to obtaine <note place="margin">Luk 11. 13</note> theſe ſpirituall graces at Gods hands.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The remedies to cure anger</hi> in others. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>ANd ſo much for the remedies which ſerue to cure anger in our ſelues: now we are to ſpeake of the remedies wherby
<pb facs="tcp:10356:84"/> wee may cure it in others. The firſt meanes to mitigate anger in another, is <note place="margin">The firſt meanes is ſilence.</note> to vſe ſilence: for as the fire cannot long continue if the wood be taken from it, ſo anger cannot long indure, if words and croſſe anſweres be not multiplyed: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the other ſide, croſſe ſpeeches and peruerſe replies, make the chollericke man proceed from anger to rage, from folly, to fury and madneſſe. And this the wiſe man teacheth vs <hi>Pro:</hi> 26. 21. <hi>As the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 62. 21</note> 
                     <hi>coale maketh burning coales and wood a fire, ſo the contentious man is apt to kindle ſtrife. So chap. the</hi> 30. <hi>and the laſt verſe. As he that wringeth his noſe cauſeth bloud to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 33.</note> 
                     <hi>come out: ſo he that forceth wrath bringeth forth ſtrife.</hi> By ſilent yeelding therfore thou mayeſt eaſely abate anothers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whereas croſſe anſweres make it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For as the Canno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhot loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his force if it light in ſoft earth or Wool, but daſheth the ſtony wal in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: ſo the violence of the moſt furious anger is abated, when it is not reſiſted, but furiouſly rageth, where it findeth any oppoſition. And hence it is that <hi>Plato</hi> calleth anger <hi>Neruos animi, qui &amp; intenderentur acerbitate, &amp; laxarentur man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine:</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:10356:84"/> The nerues or ſinewes of the minde, vvhich are intended and made ſtiffe, with ſharpneſſe &amp; bitterneſſe, but ſlacke and eaſie, with curteſie and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If therefore thou wouldeſt paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie an others wrath, follow the counſaile of Ieſus the ſonne of Syrach, <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. 4. <note place="margin">Ecclus. 8. 4</note> 
                     <hi>Contend not with a man full of words, neither heape vp wood on his fire.</hi> Where he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that as the wood increaſeth the fire, ſo multiplying of words increaſeth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>But ſilence is not alwayes expedient, eſpecially when men haue a iuſt cauſe, <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d meanes a ſoft an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</note> and an honeſt excuſe: for oftentimes the angry man will imagine, that ſilence ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth contempt; as though they were ſilent becauſe they ſcorned to returne an anſwer. And therefore the ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, namely a ſoft and milde anſwere, eyther excuſing their faulte by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their innocencie, or in all humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, confeſſing it, and crauing pardon, is more fit phyſick to cure anger in ſome natures and diſpoſitions. And this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine the wiſe Phyſition preſcribeth vs. <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. 1. <hi>A ſoft anſwere putteth away</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>wrath: but greeuous words ſtir vp anger. So Pr.</hi> 25. 15. <hi>a prince is pacified by ſtaying a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10356:85"/> 
                     <hi>&amp; a ſoft tongue breaketh the bones,</hi> or as it is in the originall, <hi>a man of bone,</hi> that is: ſuch an one as is moſt ſtife and obdurate. An example hereof we haue in <hi>Abigaile:</hi> who by her milde and diſcreet ſpeeches, quickly appeaſed <hi>Dauids</hi> furious anger. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 24. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25 24.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>As therefore Iron which is red hotte, being dipped in colde water, preſently looſeth all his heate, and returneth to his naturall coldneſſe: ſo is the heate of the hotteſt anger, ſoone mitigated with a colde &amp; milde anſwere. Wheras on the otherſide, croſſe and vntoward ſpeeches, maketh the leaſt ſparke of anger flame out into fury: as we may ſee in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> who though he were the meekeſt man liuing on the earth, as it is <hi>Num.</hi> 12. 3. yet by the contentious <note place="margin">Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 12. 3.</note> wrangling of the people, he was ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to wrath, that he grieuouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God, by ſpeaking vnaduiſedlye with his lips; as may appeare by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the twentith chapter of Numbers, <note place="margin">Num. 20. 10. 11. Pſal. 106. 32. 33.</note> the 10. &amp; 11. verſes, with the 106. <hi>Pſal.</hi> the 32 &amp; 33. ver. As therfore if a man blowe vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſparke, he maketh it increaſe to a flame, but if he ſpit vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it he quencheth
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:10356:85"/> it, and both proceede out of the mouth: ſo he that vttereth croſſe anſweres, doth make the leaſt ſparke of anger become furious rage, whereas milde and ſoft an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres do eaſily appeaſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>The laſt meanes is after his anger is ouerpaſt to geue him wholeſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle <note place="margin">The 3. meanes diſcreete admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and good admonitions, wherby he may be taught the great euils which follow anger. For as it is not fit to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Phyſicke to a ſicke patient while he is in a fit of an ague, and therefore diſcreete Phyſitions rather make choiſe of their patients good day: ſo it is in vayne for a man to ſeeke the curing of anger by good counſaile, vnleſſe he ſtay till the fit be paſſed ouer, and the heate of anger ſomwhat aſſwaged. For a man cannot, nor will not hearken to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans reaſons, while he is ſubiect to his owne paſſions. And as a man heareth nothing almoſt which is ſayd when his houſe is on fire, for the noyſe of the multitude, the crackling of the flame, and the perturbation of his owne minde
<pb facs="tcp:10356:86"/> ſo the violence of this affection, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this paſſion, doth make a man while he is in a fit of rage, deafe to all reaſon. And therefore they are to be admoniſhed when the fury hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſpent it ſelfe, and the great euils of anger both in reſpect of their ſoules and bodies, their neighbours and friends, the church and common wealth, are as it were in one view, to be preſented to their more ſober meditations.</p>
                  <p>But they who admoniſh are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that they vſe al al mildeneſſe and <note place="margin">Mildenes required in admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing an angry ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> diſcretion in their admonition, leaſt while they go about to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t anger for the time to come, they preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke it. For if they bee too auſtere and and rough in vſing too inſolent inuec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues and bitter reprehenſions, they do not onely commit them ſelues a great abſurdity, while in reprouing anger they ſhew their owne ſpleene; but alſo make their admonition altogether vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Becauſe the angry man (if he ſee them ſo ſharpe and ſeuere) will rather thinke how he may defend his fault by aggrauating the iniuries which he hath receaued, then eyther confeſſe it, to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:10356:86"/> ſuch a ſynick cenſurer or labour to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it. For as no man will ſuffer his wound to be ſearched by ſuch a ſurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as hath a rough hand, &amp; a hard hart, neyther will any patient commit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the cure of a froward and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe Phyſition: ſo no man can abide (and therefore much leſſe an angry man) to haue his gauled faults, too much rubbed, or the woundes and diſeaſes of his minde, healed and cured, with too ſharpe a corraſiue and lothſome potion of inſolent and bitter vvordes. They therefore who vvill angerly reproue anger, are no fit Phyſitions for them vvho are ſubiect to this paſſion. For to ſuch they vvill eyther hide and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their imperfections, rather fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelues vvell, then they will diſcouer their diſeaſe to ſuch a crabbed Phyſition; or els they will iuſtifie, and defend them as lawfull and neceſſarie. And as the feareful ſnake, when he hath noe meanes to flye away, vvill turne agayne, and deſperately leape into the face of him that purſueth him: or as the tymorous Stagge, vvhen
<pb facs="tcp:10356:87"/> he can eſcape noe longer by running maketh a ſtand, turning cowardly feare into deſperate rage. So the angry man being ſo hardly purſued with ſharpe inuectiues and bitter reprehenſions, that he hath no euaſion of excuſe to couer his fault, nor hope of pity by confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, doth as it were flye into the fare of the reprouer, by obiecting his greater faults, that they may ſerue to extenuate his, which are leſſe, You (wil he ſay) who ſo ſharpely reproue me for my choller, haue other faultes as great as this, and therefore you may do well to cure your ſelfe before you become anothers Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Yea in this you would ſhew your ſelf no more innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, if you had the like occaſion to ſhew your anger. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you ſeeme in your conuerſation ſweet &amp; harmles, yet he that ſhould taſt you would not finde you free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaule, hee that ſhould handle you ſomewhat roughly, would ſoone perceiue by his owne ſmart that you haue a ſting, though you do not thruſt it out being not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked. In a word the angry man wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cry <hi>peccaui,</hi> vnleſſe afterwardes with ſome confidence he may adde <hi>miſcrere</hi>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:10356:87"/> neyther will he ſuffer his wounds to be cured by ſuch an one, who by his rough handling will more vex him, then plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him by the cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much for the remedies and <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> medicines which we are to vſe for the curing of anger, eyther in our ſelues or others, which I would wiſh euery one who finde themſelues ſubiect to this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carefully to apply vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: for as it will not benefit a ſicke man to reade his Phyſitions preſcript, or to carry the medicine in his pocket, vnleſſe he take and receiue it according to his direction: ſo will this Phyſicke of the ſoule little auayle for the curing of anger vnleſſe it be applied to the heart and conſcience. But ſeeing we are not able ſo much as once to think a good <note place="margin">2. Co. 3. 5. Phi. 2. 13.</note> thought, as of our ſelues, but it is God onely which worketh in vs both the will and the deede: let vs intreate the Lord who is the onely true Phyſition, that he will not onely vouchſafe to anoynt the blinde eyes of our vnderſtanding with
<pb facs="tcp:10356:88"/> the precious eye ſalue of his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that we may ſee the deformities of this and all other diſordered affections. And alſo that hee will with the ſame ſpirite inable vs, to reforme and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue them; that theyr violence and fury beeing abated, and the corruption and filthyneſſe of them being purged, cleanſed, and ſanctified, they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fit and ſeruiceable, for the ſetting foorth of his glory, the good of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, and the furthering of our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſaluation. Which grace he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaufe vnto vs, who died for vs, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, to vvhom vvith the father and the holy ghoſt, be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all honour and glory, principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, power and dominion, for euer and euer.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:10356:88"/>
            <head>Faultes eſcaped.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Epiſt. to the reader. page 2. line. 19. for <hi>he</hi> reade <hi>the.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ibi. li. 23. for <hi>doth,</hi> reade <hi>doe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pa. 2. b. li. 27. for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, reade <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Pa. 63. a. li. 23. for <hi>is,</hi> reade <hi>his.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>pa. 71. 1. li. 22. reade <hi>roaring Lion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>pa. 72. b. li. 16. read <hi>the firſt meanes.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
